government television.
Good afternoon everybody.
Welcome to the APRIL 15th 2025
regular meeting of the san
francisco board of supervisors
.
>> MADAM Clerk, will you please
call the roll?
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor chin chin present
supervisor chin chin present
supervisor dorsey dorsey
present supervisor and engardio
and gaudio present supervisor
fielder fielder present
supervisor mahmood mahmood
presents supervisor mendelssohn
present mendelssohn present
supervisor melgar melgar
present supervisor sartor
sartor present supervisors
cheryl cheryl present
and supervisor walton walton
present MR. PRESIDENT all
members are present.
>> thank you MADAM Clerk.
>> the san francisco board of
supervisors acknowledges that
we are on the unceded ancestral
homeland of the roma saloni who
are the original inhabitants of
the san francisco peninsula as
the indigenous stewards of this
land and in accordance with
their traditions the roma to
shallowness have never ceded
loss nor forgotten their
responsibilities as the
caretakers of this place as
well as for all peoples who
reside in their traditional
territory as guests we
recognize that we benefit from
living and working on their
traditional homelands.
we wish to pay our respects by
acknowledging the ancestors,
elders and relatives of the
roma aloni community and by
affirming their sovereign
rights as first peoples.
>> colleagues, please please
join me in saying the pledge of
allegiance.
I pledge allegiance to the flag
of the united states of america
and to the republic for which
it stands one nation under GOD
indivisible with liberty
and justice for all.
>> on behalf of the board I
want to acknowledge the staff
at S.F. Gov tv and especially
james cohen at today who record
each of our meetings and make
the transcripts transcripts
available to the public online
.
>> and with that, MADAM Clerk,
should we go to our 2 P.M.
Special order?
>> yes, MR. PRESIDENT.
Special order at 2 P.M. Is the
appearance by the honorable
mayor daniel lurie.
There being no questions
submitted from eligible members
of the board, the mayor MAY
address the board for up to
five minutes.
>> welcome, MR. Mayor.
Thank you, board PRESIDENT.
Man, woman and members of the
board of supervisors.
>> this week at least for some
of us marks 100 days in office
and it offers us an opportunity
to reflect on the work we've
started and everything that we
still want to achieve.
We have made public safety the
number one priority.
Working relentlessly to provide
clean and safe streets,
confront the deadly fentanyl
crisis head on and connect
people on the street to
treatment and care.
At the same time we are laying
the groundwork to jumpstart our
economy in our downtown core
along our commercial corridors
and across our neighborhoods.
I believe we're off to a strong
start thanks in large part to
the collaboration and support
of this board.
Together we pass the fentanyl
state of emergency ordinance
expedited legislation to unlock
federal funds for critical
infrastructure and health
projects and advanced
legislation to spur housing
development in soma
and downtown.
We introduce new legislation to
expand our entertainment zones
and renew the first year free
program to support small
businesses.
And we announce two major
executive directives permit
S.F. And breaking the cycle.
Property crime is down 35% from
last year.
Violent crime is down 15%
and car break ins are at 22
year lows.
Muni ridership is back at 75%
of 2019 levels and for the
first time in years people feel
san francisco is headed in the
right direction.
So much of the progress we've
made as a city stems from a
major change right here at city
hall.
The new era of collaboration is
real.
We prove it to san franciscans
every day.
When you call me about a
legislative idea or when I step
into one of your offices and we
solve problems on the spot.
Let's be clear we're just
getting started.
In the coming months we're
going to pass our family zoning
plan to make sure families can
live in our city for
generations.
We will pass a budget that puts
our city on the path to fiscal
sustainability.
And we will add the interim
housing capacity we need to
give people on the street a
better option.
And just as we've worked side
by side these past almost 100
days, I want to firm my
commitment to all of you that I
will work side by side with you
for as long as I am in office.
Thank you very much.
>> thanks for having me.
Thank you.
Thank you, MR. Mayor, for
joining us today.
The matter has been discussed
and is now filed.
>> thank you.
All right.
Thank you.
All right, MADAM Clerk, let's
go back to communications.
>> do we have any
communications?
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
The san francisco board of
supervisors welcomes your
attendance here in the board's
legislative chamber.
>> you MAY also watch the
proceeding on S.F. Gop tv's
channel 20 six or view the live
stream at w w w dot S.F. Geo v
vtv.Org if you have public
public comment you'd like to
submit in writing send an email
to be offset as have g o v dawg
or via us postal service to the
san francisco board of
supervisors.
>> the number one DR. Carlton b
good place city hall room 244
san francisco, california 94102
if you need to request a
reasonable accommodation under
the americans with disabilities
act or you need language
assistance, contact the clerk's
office at least two business
days in advance by calling
(415) 554-5184.
>> that concludes my comments,
MR. PRESIDENT.
All right.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Let's go to approval of our
meeting minutes.
>> approval of the MARCH 11th
2025 board meeting minutes.
>> okay, so we have our MARCH
I'm sorry MARCH 11th.
>> yes, MARCH 11th, 20 25 got
us our MARCH 11th regular board
meeting minutes.
I don't see anyone with changes
.
Can I have a motion to approve
the minutes as presented move
by chan is and seconded by
cheryl.
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call the roll on the motion on
the minutes supervisor chin
chin eyes supervisor chin chin
eyes supervisor dorsey dorsey
eyes supervisor and engardio
and engardio I supervisor
fielder fielder I supervisor my
good mahmood I supervisor
mandolin hi mandolin I
supervisor melgar melgar I
supervisor sartor sartor I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
and supervisor walton walton I
there are 11 eyes without
objection the minutes will be
approved after public comment
as presented MS. M clerk let's
go to our consent agenda items
one through six items one
through six are on consent.
>> these items are considered
to be routine if a member
objects an item MAY be removed
and considered separately.
>> I don't see anyone on the
roster so no MADAM Clerk can
you call the roll on items one
through six supervisor chin
chin eyes supervisor chin chin
I supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor and engardio
and engardio I supervisor
fielder fielder I supervisor
mahmood mahmood I supervisor
randleman all right mandel men
I supervisor melgar melgar
absent supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
and supervisor walton walton I
there are ten eyes one absence
all right these ordinances are
finally passed MADAM Clerk can
you take us to our regular
agenda unfinished business item
number seven item seven this is
an ordinance to amend the
planning code and the zoning
map to establish the 600
townsend street west special
use district to allow the
legalization of the
longstanding office uses at the
site and to waive or reduce the
bicycle parking open space
streetscape transportation
demand management and impact
fee requirements and to affirm
the cycle determination and to
make the appropriate findings.
>> all right.
I think we can take that item
same house, same call.
>> this ordinance is finally
passed.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item eight?
Item eight this is an ordinance
to amend the administrative
code to create the castro upper
market entertainment zone
and to clarify the boundaries
of the existing area
entertainment zone and to
affirm the second
determination.
>> and we'll take this item
same house, same call without
objection, the ordinance is
finally passed and MADAM Clerk,
please take us to item nine.
>> item nine is an ordinance to
approve and waive competitive
solicitation obligations for a
board commission.
Barclays and loan for china
basin park and for a management
agreement for adjacent public
and open spaces between the
port and an affiliate of
seawall lot 337 associates llc
developer of the mission rock
project and to approve a port
commission license with mission
rock utilities inc and to
approve to port commission
licenses and and absolving
services agreement with pacific
gas and electric company to
facilitate gas services to
private property in the project
area and electric power service
to the third street bridge
pilot house and to affirm the
second determination and to
make the appropriate findings.
>> and we will take this item
same house, same call without
objection this ordinance is
passed on first reading MADAM
Clerk can you please call item
ten?
>> item ten this is a
resolution to approve
and authorize the general
manager of the san francisco
public utilities commission to
execute the first amendment to
a professional services
agreement for construction
management services for the
east bay region with cpms C.M.
Perot's joint venture to
increase the amount by 25
million for a new total amount
of 34 million and contract
increase by two years for a new
total contract duration of nine
years through JUNE 3rd, 2030.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you call
the roll on this item on item
ten?
Supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor and engardio
and engardio eyes supervisor
fielder fielder I supervisor
mahmood mahmood I supervisor
mandolin I edelman eyes
supervisor melgar melgar I
supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
and supervisor walton walton
either are lebanese without
objection this resolution is
adopted MADAM Clerk please call
item 11 item 11 this is a
resolution to retroactively
approve and authorize the
director of property on behalf
of the department of
homelessness and support of
housing to execute a lease of
real property with lombard
hotel group for the use of the
monarch hotel located at 1015
geary street for a non
congregate temporary shelter
program with 102 units for a
one year term APRIL 1st 2025
through MARCH 31st 2026 with an
annual base rent of 1.6 million
and a final payment of
approximately 100,000 upon
surrender of the property
and to affirm the second
determination and to make the
appropriate findings I think we
can take this item same house,
same call without objection the
resolution is adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk please call item
12 item 12 this is a resolution
to approve and authorize the
general manager of the public
utilities commission to execute
a first amendment to the first
professional services agreement
specialized and technical as
needed services for operations
and maintenance support with
stantec j h c g mmd jv aecom w
r e g and lee incorporated to
increase each contract by 5.5
million each with a new not to
exceed amount of 13 million for
a total a new total of 52
million across all four
contracts with no changes to
the terms or duration of the
period of the contract through
AUGUST 29th 2020 eight.
>> let's take this item same
house, same call without
objection the resolution is
adopted.
And MADAM Clerk, can you please
call items 13 through 15
together items 13 through 15
are three resolutions that
approve grant amendments
between the department of
homelessness and supportive
housing and various entities
for item 13 this is the first
amendment to the grant
agreement with abode services
for adult rapid rehousing to
extend the term by 24 months
for a new total term JANUARY
1st 2023 through JUNE 30th 2027
to increase the agreement
amount by 8.5 million for a new
total of 18.4 million for item
14.
This approves the fourth
amendment to the grant
agreement with episcopal
community services for property
management and support of
services at the henry hotel for
supportive housing to extend
the grant term by 24 months for
a new total term JULY 1st 2019
through JUNE 30th 2027 to
increase the agreement amount
by approximately 5.8 million
for a new total amount of 20.4
million item 15 this approves
the second amendment to the
grant agreement with five keys
schools and programs for the
art minor hotel for supportive
housing for six transitional
aged youth to extend the grant
term by 24 months for a new
total term of JUNE 1st 2021
through JUNE 30th 2027 to
increase the agreement amount
by 4.9 million for a new total
amount of 13.9 million and for
item oh that was the last item,
MR. PRESIDENT.
>> all right.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
I think we can take these items
same house, same call without
objection these resolutions are
adopted and then MADAME Clerk,
can you please call item 16?
>> item 16.
This is a resolution to adopt
the city and county of san
francisco ten year capital
expenditure plan for fiscal
year 2026 through 2035 pursuant
to the administrative code
section 3.20 all right.
We can take this item same
house, same call without
objection the resolutions
adopted MADAM Clerk, please
call item 17.
>> item 17 this is a resolution
to approve the second amendment
to the grant agreement between
mission action inc and the
department of homelessness
and support of housing for
emergency shelter to extend the
term by 24 months for a new
total term JULY 1st 2021
through JUNE 30th 2027 to
increase the agreement amount
by approximately 8.5 million
for a new total amount of 18.5
million and we can take this
item same house, same call
without objection the
resolutions adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item 18 item 18 this is a
resolution to approve a lease
with the chinatown community
children's center for
approximately 6372 a square
feet of real property located
within city hall and its
grounds a pertinent at a base
rent of $1 per year to
authorize the director of
property upon receipt of the
approved permits for the
construction of tenant
improvements to the leased
premises to execute a lease on
behalf of the city for an
initial ten year term with 210
year options to renew and we
can take this item same house
same call without objection the
resolution is adopted.
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call items 19 through 22
together items 19 through 22 or
for the sunnydale housing
revenue notes and loan
agreements items 19 and 20 or 2
resolutions that are approved
for purposes of the internal
revenue code of 1986 as amended
to multifamily housing revenue
bonds for item 19 this
authorizes the execution
and delivery of a multifamily
housing revenue note in one or
more series in an aggregate
principal amount of 53.3
million to provide financing
for the construction of an 89
unit multifamily rental housing
project located at 65 santos
street known as the sunnydale
hope as of blocks seven four
and 20 this authorizes the
issuance, sale and delivery of
multifamily family housing
revenue bonds in one or more
series of approximately 57
million for the purpose to
provide financing to construct
a 95 unit multifamily rental
housing project located at 1652
sunnydale avenue known as
sunnydale hope as have block
nine and to approve the form
and to authorize the execution
of multiple agreements for both
items for items 21 and 22 these
are two resolutions that
approve and authorize the
mayor's office of housing
and community development to
execute an amended and restated
loan agreement item 21 with the
sunnydale block seven housing
partners lp for a total loan
amount of 18 million to finance
the construction of an 89 unit
multifamily rental housing
development for low income
households to be known as the
sunnydale hope S.F. Block seven
and for item 22 with the
sunnydale block nine housing
partners lp for a total loan
amount of 30.2 million to
finance the construction of a
95 unit multifamily rental
housing development for low
income households to be known
as the sunnydale hope S.F.
Block nine and to adopt the
appropriate findings for both
items.
>> and we can take these items
same house, same call without
objection these resolutions are
adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk can you please
call item 23?
Item 23 this is an ordinance to
amend the planning code to
expand criteria for certain
self-storage uses in the
production distribution
and repair zoning district
and to extend the sunset date
for such uses and to affirm the
secret determination and to
make the appropriate findings.
>> we'll take this item same
house, same call without
without objection this
ordinance is passed on first
reading MADAM Clerk can you
call items 24th through 27
together items 24 through 27 or
for items that pertain to the
mission rock project item 24
this ordinance exempts
irrevocable offers of public
infrastructure associated with
the mission road project phase
one a it also establishes the
official public right of way
widths and street grids to
amend ordinance number 1061
entitled regulating the width
of sidewalks to establish the
official sidewalk width on the
above referenced streets
and adopt the appropriate
findings.
Item 25 this ordinance amends
the public works code to
designate the port of san
francisco in place of the
department of public works as
the responsible party for
permitting tables, seating
and other minor encroachments
on the public sidewalk at the
mission rock pier 70
and potrero power station
projects and to affirm the
second determination and to
make the appropriate findings
for item 26 this ordinance
grants revokable master
encroachment permit to mission
rock utilities inc a delaware
corporation to maintain
encroachments on and beneath
the public right of way on
portions of terry francois
boulevard bridge view way DR.
Maya angelou lane tony stone
crossing third street
and longbridge street within
the adjacent to the mission
rock special use district
and to make the appropriate
findings and for item 27 this
resolution grants revokable
permission to the port to
maintain encroachments in the
public right of way and to
adopt the appropriate findings
.
And we can take these items
same house same same call
without objection or the
audiences are passed on first
reading and the resolution is
adopted.
>> and MADAM Clerk, can you
please call item 28 item 28
this is a resolution to
preserve east clementina street
and east tehama street as
official street names for an
area from the embarcadero
westward to first street
and specifically naming the yet
to be constructed one block
segment of east clementina
and east to hama streets
between main and beal streets
that currently are slated for
public improvement
and dedication as public right
of way as part of the transbay
redevelopment plan.
And we'll take this item same
house, same call without
objection the resolution is
adopted.
madame clerk please call item
number 29 item 20 nine this
ordinance amending the
administrative code to change
the annual economic statement
of city funded organizations
requirements to limit the
application of nonprofit
reporting requirements to
organizations receiving more
than 1 million annually to
reduce required information
types and permit redaction of
information to avoid personal
harm.
We can take this item same
house, same call without
objection the ordinance is
passed on first reading MADAME
Clerk can you please call item
30?
>> item 30 this is a motion to
appoint supervisor matt dorsey
to the san francisco bay
conservation and development
commission for an indefinite
term or to the conclusion of
his term as a member of the
board of supervisors.
>> colleagues can I have a
motion to excuse supervisor
dorsey from voting on this item
moved by chan seconded by
mahmud and we can take that
without objection.
Supervisor dorsey is excused
and then colleagues nobody has
anything to say about this.
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call the roll on item 30?
Supervisor chan chan I
supervisor chin chin I
supervisor and gaudio
and gaudio I supervisor fielder
fielder I supervisor mahmood
mahmood I supervisor mendelson
hi mendelson I supervisor
melgar melgar I supervisor sadr
sadr I supervisor cheryl cheryl
I and supervisor walton walton
i there are ten attorneys
without objection this motion
is approved.
MADAM Clerk can you please call
item 31?
>> item 31 this is a motion to
appoint melinda burris
and presently patel to these
sugary drinks distributor tax
advisory committee terms ending
DECEMBER 31st 2026 please call
the roll on item 31 supervisor
chan chin I supervisor chin
chin I supervisor dorsey dorsey
I supervisor and gaudio
and gaudio I supervisor fielder
fielder I supervisor mahmood
mahmood I supervisor mendelson
I mandolin I supervisor melgar
melgar I supervisor sartor sadr
I supervisor cheryl cheryl I
and supervisor walton walton I
there are 11 eyes without
objection this motion is
approved MADAM Clerk can you
please call item 32 item 32
this is a motion to appoint
estella ortiz to the sheriff's
department oversight board term
ending MARCH 1st 2029.
We can take 32.
Same house, same call.
Without objection this motion
is approved.
MADAM Clerk can you please call
item 33?
>> item 33 resolution to accept
the san francisco sheriff's
office military equipment use
policy for 2020 for the annual
report and inventory and to
approve the request for
purchase and use of additional
equipment consistent with the
criteria set forth in state
law.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call the roll on this item on
item 33 supervisor chin chin no
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey eyes
supervisor and engardio
and engardio I supervisor
fielder fielder no supervisor
mahmood mahmood I supervisor
mendelson I mandolin I
supervisor melgar melgar I
supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
and supervisor walton walton no
there are eight eyes and three
nos with supervisors chan
fielder and walton voting no
the resolution is adopted MADAM
Clerk I guess we could do two
minutes of roll call.
Okay.
First up to introduce new
business is supervisor chen for
two minutes.
>> I will try.
Thank you.
MADAM Clerk and colleagues.
Today I am introducing
legislation to grant our fire
department the sole source
contracting authority to
purchase fire apparatus fire
engines that are best equipped
for our specific san francisco
trains and buildings recently
the new york times has reported
that fire engines, fire trucks
manufacturing across the
country is monopolized by three
companies and the orders can
take years to fulfill this
authority.
Sole source contracting will
how fast track engines and fire
trucks for our fire department
to ensure that they are up to
the job of our san francisco
streets our fire firefighters
are always first on the scene
of our emergency but with the
aging of trucks some of which
are still in operation from
1970s, this legislation will
give our fire department the
ability to acquire fire
firefighting apparatus equipped
with the most up to date
technology and equipment that
will really meet their
challenges any disaster that
will come our way.
>> but this legacy ation is not
the only legislation in the
part of a larger series of
legislation being introduced
today in partnership with
mayor lurie and for PRESIDENT
Mendelsohn to also allow the
fire department to seek
partnership to a funding to
invest in this vital
infrastructure and to protect
our firefighters not just with
that equipment but also with
cancer testing kits.
So with that the rest I will
submit and I look forward to
having your support colleagues
thank you.
Supervisor chan MR. PRESIDENT,
let's go to our 230 special
order.
>> it's now time for
meritorious service
commendations to members of the
who are here in the public
gallery and we will start with
district one supervisor chan
thank you, PRESIDENT And so
colleagues today I'm very
excited about this and I hope
that you will join me
in welcoming roger pinkham,
executive director of the great
star theater and celebrating a
great star theater's 100th
anniversary.
This although not located
in the richmond it's located
in chinatown where I grew up as
a kid and where my aunt was a
she's an avid cantonese opera
singer.
wow.
Today she's long retired but
this recognition and where she
and I really hung out at great
star theater when I was growing
up it's a very meaningful space
for the two of us.
We often go there for movies,
matinee time and then we will
go to our early dinner
together.
I just just think that the
great start theater means so
much for our community.
>> it's a symbolism behind
every movie's every
performances in in that space
and great star also formerly
known as great china theater
was originally built as a
chinese opera house in 1925.
For centuries chinese opera was
a primary form of entertainment
in china and within the chinese
diaspora serving as a powerful
medium for telling stories of
the chinese people at the time
not only has great star been a
significant cultural
and entertainment hub for
chinatown, it is where families
make memories like mine where
and where community was built.
The great star theater became
the cultural center and a
powerhouse for the chinese
american community.
In addition to entertainment,
the great star was also a venue
for community town halls
protest and political events
for causes both local and for
great start later expanded to
showing chinese movies
and american short films while
still reserving the theater for
operas for special cultural
celebrations like dragon ball
and the autumn moon festival.
Bruce lee's very first film
when he was just an infant at
the time was also shown at
great star.
But in 2021 there are some
brave souls alex chu and roger
pinkham reopened the venue
and created great, great star
theater as a nonprofit
organization with a mission to
continue a great star's legacy
in cultivating traditional
asian performing arts,
nurturing emerging artists,
revitalizing the community
and promoting economic growth.
>> and the reason why I say
that they're brave souls as you
MAY recall 2021 we were at the
peak of pandemic and yet they
took on that responsibility
and they took on that mission
in its renew form grace star
theater now hosts many, many
different kinds of performance
very diverse that embraces even
more voices through modern
cabaret.
Wow.
Comedy and film as well as
cantonese opera and gongs our
music.
Thank you alice and roger for
the theater to really restoring
it to its former glory and and
going as far as commissioning
costume porcelain tiles from
china to match to original
color and texture and the
dedication in building on to a
great start 100 year history as
a performing arts and cultural
mecca colleagues we also have
the opportunity to vote on a
resolution today recognizing
the great star theater's
centennial celebration.
And I also want to thank my
colleagues supervisor souder
and also congratulations who
was a new dad and also
supervisor chin will present
amendment and supervisor
fielder for your co-sponsorship
and before turning this floor
to the great stars theater
stars, I'm going to turn it
over to supervisor souder.
Thank you supervisor jan for
bestowing this well-deserved
honor upon the great star
theater this as supervisor
chang shared this is a
institution that has meant a
lot to chinatown and has meant
a lot to generations of
families, generations of
families throughout san
francisco and particularly
in chinatown have enjoyed
performances of all types at
great star theater and you're
making sure that that can
continue hopefully for another
100 years.
Roger and alice, I want to
thank you for your commitment
and your investment.
I know it is a significant
undertaking and you've poured a
lot of time and money and sweat
and tears into that theater.
The community recognizes it, we
see it and we're all enjoying
it.
So thank you for all of your
work in making sure that this
theater has been reborn
and continues to serve san
francisco.
>> thank you.
Thank you all.
This is a huge honor.
We are so honored.
And also, you know, just we
really feel the responsibility
of maintaining this beautiful
historic theater.
I hope most of you had a chance
to check it out by now but it
is 100 years old and it's crazy
that it survived so long.
It's actually not just the
oldest chinese theater in san
francisco.
It's the oldest chinese theater
in north america.
So we are very proud to have
that here in san francisco
and to be carrying forward its
legacy.
It is not easy but we put our
blood, sweat and tears into it
literally it's been it's been a
journey and we're so happy that
we all get to continue this
journey together.
>> and thank you everyone.
I'm so honored to be here be
part of this and thank you for
recognizing our work and then
the community effort.
It has been an incredible
journey.
Was everyone and every time
when I think about what
happened 100 years ago and now
this responsibility is on our
shoulder I feel very lucky
and special to take on this
mission moving it forward
and thank you so much for
recognize our work
right district seven supervisor
melgar thank you so much
PRESIDENT Mandell man and so
today I have the great honor of
doing a commendation for the
city college men's basketball
team so dominating.
>> thank you so much.
Welcome.
Athletic director brown coach
justin labar.
>> chancellor bailey I know is
here.
Trustee zamora is here.
The audience as well at dean
cowper and all of the members
of the city college rams on
their dominant 70 5 to 58
victory over folger fullerton
college to win the 2025
california community college
athletic association men's
basketball state championship.
>> this victory capped a 32 to
1 season for the rams.
>> the second 32 win season
in the last three years.
>> that's pretty good.
It marks city college's sixth
state title.
>> coach leyva has built more
than just a winning program.
He has built a dynasty grounded
in teamwork, defense
and community pride.
The rams incredible run titles
2011 2016 2018, 2020 two
and 2025 shows what's possible
when public education, asian
and athletics are supported
and celebrated.
>> city college of san
francisco continues to be a
source of inspiration
and opportunity for our
residents.
>> proving that talent thrives
in accessible public
institutions, the championship
underscores the value of
investing in community
colleges.
The rams success came from
tenacious defense out
rebounding fullerton
and holding them to a season
low in scoring coast north
player of the year and state
tournament mvp myles amos led
the charge with strong
contributions from ricky
mitchell junior and john
squire.
This championship is a win for
our entire city.
It reflects the grit, diversity
and perseverance that define
san francisco.
so let's take a moment to
celebrate the athletes coaching
staff, families and fans who
made it all possible.
Thank you so much.
>> up just the team.
>> all right, coach, thank you.
Thanks for having us.
You know, city college is not
in the news that many that much
for positive stuff.
So this is really nice to be
acknowledged by you guys
because it is a big positive
and a lot of these kids went to
high school saying nation
naci's sacred heart reared
in stuart hall and then a
couple of marine guys.
But all these guys basically
are from northern california.
>> yeah.
So it's it's really nice.
We had an incredible season
and we're just very thankful
that you guys acknowledged us.
It's really nice of you.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
We hope you don't have to.
All the schoolchildren want
coaches not that this year we
should not just try to get
them.
We always will going to be
going oh it was okay go rams
well look at it the junior
college going to center all
right surprise the walton's
going to let me go ahead I am
wondering if nicole workman
and kathy osorio are in the
chamber and I am not
interesting.
All right.
Well, looks like the date ended
ten honorees are MAY not be
here.
Okay.
All right.
we're going to we're going to
kill time for a moment while
the yep, there's the chief.
>> all right.
D-10 supervisor walton hey,
thank you so much.
>> PRESIDENT Mendham
in colleagues today I rise to
recognize and commend chief
bill scott for his extra
ordinary service and courageous
leadership she's got.
>> can you point to chief today
we honor you for your
unwavering commitment to
building a safer and more just
san francisco.
>> chief scott was sworn in as
chief of police on JANUARY
23rd, 2017 after serving 27
years with the los angeles
police department where he rose
to the rank of deputy chief.
From the moment he stepped into
leadership here in san
francisco, he has been guided
by a clear and powerful vision
to implement meaningful reform
rooted in 21st century policing
principles centered on
accountability, transparency
and trust.
Under his leadership, the san
francisco police department
became a national model for
reform.
What began as 272
recommendations from the obama
era U.S. Department of justice
became a blueprint for
transforming even after the
first trump administration
abandoned the project.
Chief scott refused to let the
work go unfinished.
Instead he brought in the
california department of
justice to ensure oversight,
integrity and a commitment to
completion.
on APRIL 1st, 2024, the spd
submitted its final response is
an extraordinary milestone
that's cements chiefs scott's
legacy of reform.
Chief scott's time at the helm
has not been without challenge.
He led this city through a
global pandemic and a national
reckoning on police following
the murder of george floyd.
>> throughout it all he
remained steady and committed
to safety, to justice and to
the communities most impacted
by both crime and systemic
inequality.
Thanks to his leadership, san
francisco's violent crime rates
remain well below those of
other major cities in our
clearance rates for serious
crimes like homicides far
exceed national averages.
Beyond the badge.
Chief scott is a father, a
husband and a proud son of
birmingham, alabama and a
graduate of the university of
alabama.
His commitment to public
service has always been deeply
personal and it shows
in everything he has done for
san francisco.
And even though we don't always
agree on policy and strategy, I
can say that you represent the
department and this city in a
manner that demonstrates you
care about people
and community.
You have a hard job and always
managed to focus on what is
important and that is keeping
san francisco safe.
We are glad you are chief
and stand by your leadership.
We honor you not just for your
accomplishments before the
integrity empathy and courage
you bring to the role you have
laid the groundwork for a
department that continues to
evolve continues to reform
and continues to serve our city
with dignity.
So today we give you your
flowers and your donuts while
you can if you and I know we
have and I know supervisor
dorsey wants to say a few words
thank you supervisor walton I
really want to thank my
colleague supervisor walton for
honoring chief scott's
leadership today and also for
bringing that universally
acknowledged reward for
excellence in policing donuts.
As part of the certification
and tradition going I also want
to add my own expression of
gratitude to you chief for
leading our city's police
department through the nation's
most ambitious effort for 21st
century police reforms.
I assume as many of you know,
chief bill scott was my boss
just three short years ago
and although we only worked
together for two years, it was
among the most consequential
times for law enforcement
in modern history.
Against the backdrop of the
murder of george floyd and a
once in a century pandemic at a
moment when law enforcement
really nationwide needed moral
leadership, you spoke so
powerfully about your own
background that inspired your
own career as a reformer.
As someone who grew up
in birmingham, alabama learning
about the civil rights struggle
from your own family members as
someone whose father in law
served as a schoolteacher
and pallbearer for three of the
four little black girls from
the 16th street baptist church
and as someone whose own career
began at the lapd at a moment
when it was beset by crisis
in the early 90s over the
brutality against rodney king
and the L.A. Riots that
followed to know bill scott is
to understand why police reform
matters and I am grateful for
the leadership you have brought
to the city.
It was among the greatest
honors of my career to work
with you as a civilian member
of your command staff and now
as a member of the board of
supervisors and I hope we
continue working together chief
in the years to come.
>> thanks.
Thank you.
They are really doing that.
Is mississippi delta state that
true?
>> let the chiefs speak.
>> I actually thought you were
calling for a little bit of a
relief for the chief to come
in here and not have to talk
but go ahead, chief scott.
>> thank you, PRESIDENT.
Management supervisor walton,
supervisor dorsey and the
entire board thank you for for
this honor.
It really I can't tell you how
much I appreciate this but I
also would not be standing here
if it weren't for the folks
sitting here to my left and the
community sitting behind me
and the all the members of the
speedy who are actually out
there doing the work day in and
day out.
i mean I'm honored and feel
it's such a privilege to be the
leader of this organization.
But the work is done and the
feel and it's really a
privilege to be a part of the
city and to be among you
and thank you for all your
support and just thank you.
Good job chocolate ladies.
All right.
Let's let's trade district
eight.
One more time.
Our nicole workman and kathy as
kathy azaro in the chamber tax
man who received.
>> okay let's get.
Hello let's get kathy
and nicole maybe up here.
>> all right.
Director carroll, good to see
you folks.
>> it's national public safety
telecommunications week.
>> well, who or dispatcher week
for short.
And today in recognition of
this event, I'm offering a
special commendation to kathy
osorio and nicole workman for
their decades of service with
the san francisco department of
emergency management.
Kathy has worked for dcm for 20
years.
In DECEMBER she received the
dispatcher of the year award
for her excellent handling of a
complicated vehicle pursuits.
She was notified of a license
plate match on a stolen vehicle
associated with a wanted felon
and bayview based on an
automated license plate reader.
A police motorcycle unit soon
spotted the stolen vehicle
and kathy alerted the proper
citywide channels to assist
ingleside units as well as the
california highway patrol when
the vehicle got onto the one on
one after nearly hitting an
officer on a motorcycle, the
suspect bailed on foot where
she was later apprehended by a
plainclothes officer.
Kathy's work that day kept
police officers safe and helped
to apprehend a dangerous felon.
Nicole has worked a team for
ten years and has made
significant contributions to
dbms computer assisted dispatch
projects.
She was one of the few tagalog
certified personnel there
and is proud to be able to
serve the filipino community.
Her leadership and willingness
to share her knowledge led to
her receiving the 2024 tony
hardly award for excellence
in supervision.
The award is named after the
late tony hardley who was seen
as a mother figure to many san
francisco dispatchers.
And nicole was nominated by her
peers to receive the award.
One coworker observed that she
empowers others with
information rather than
gatekeeping and reveling in her
expertise.
>> kathy and nicole are both
extraordinary public servants
and it is a privilege to be
honored to honor them here
today and director carol, did
you want to say a few things
before we let them talk to us?
>> okay.
Director carol, very briefly I
want to thank you for having us
again this year.
We it's my favorite week of the
year when we get to really kind
of draw the curtain back from
the 911 dispatcher and we get
to show you the incredible work
that these folks do every day
24 hours a day.
>> I'm thrilled to have you
hear from these two incredible
women.
In an age when public service
is has, you know, gone through
some bruises, I have never met
a group of people that more
embody the words of public
service than and I'm one one
dispatchers and you've heard a
little bit about what these
folks have done.
>> nicole and kathy to get this
award which by the way they
were nominated by their peers
which makes it all the more
special.
But what they both bring
and what comes out for me is
their selfless ness.
The last year and a half we've
gone well really the last five
years have been have been
challenging for many reasons
but particularly the last year
and a half we've lost a number
of our very loved members
suddenly and kathy has really
been there for everyone
and nicole is known as the
person that shares knowledge
absolutely selflessly.
So selflessness is the thing
that comes to mind with both of
these folks.
It is truly a family at 911
sometimes a little
dysfunctional but mostly we
love each other a lot and these
guys empower and embody that.
So I just want to thank you so
much for allowing them to come
up and say a few things.
>> thank you.
>> thank you, director.
>> hi, I'm nicole and good
afternoon.
so I'd like to begin by
sincerely thanking the board
and the voters of the city of
san francisco for passing
proposition I.
You're basically allowing us to
retire under the miscellaneous
public safety pension which
means a great deal for us.
>> so thank you so much.
Yeah.
>> yes, I'm incredibly honored
and humbled to accept the
supervisor of the year award.
It's a huge privilege to serve
a very exceptional group of
people and to you recognized by
them for that work means a lot
to me to being a91 dispatcher
is more than a job.
It's a calling.
It demands heart resilience,
unwavering commitment to the
safety of our city and our
first responders.
>> it means staying calm when
others are in crisis.
>> it means answering calls
that change lives and a lot of
times it changes us.
The past few years have brought
challenges both professionally
and personally to church street
and while it is said that you
can't pour from an empty cup
I've seen my dispatch family do
so every day with a smile
and usually with a caffeinated
drink or four.
>> today I pay tribute to the
san francisco 91 call takers
and dispatchers who has gone
home tired with a heavy heart.
They work countless hours
overtime, hours voluntary
and mandatory.
They missed holidays, birthdays
and for a lot of those people
they would work double shifts
and somehow make it to baseball
games, dance recitals, family
functions.
They are unsung heroes and this
award basically is for them.
>> I am very, very proud of my
dispatcher family and they
continue to show up for each
other.
They are kind, they are
generous and even while
navigating personal losses of
their own whether we are
mourning a parent, a spouse, a
child or one of our own they
never let life interrupt the
essential services that they
provide.
I see you guys.
I admire you and I'm endlessly
grateful for all of you.
You are my I your why I show up
every day.
>> I have a lot of people to
think to my fellow supervisors
who work magic with the
schedule every day and for
bouncing every curve ball
thrown your way and for showing
up with grit and grace.
>> thank you to the the upper
management who decided to hire
me and trusted me with projects
the center is in a period of
transition and we continue to
grow and evolve as a dispatch
center.
>> please let let's never
forget that our people the
well-being of our members they
must remain at the heart of
everything that we do.
>> they are our greatest asset
.
>> I also want to express deep
gratitude to our public safety
partners the courageous men
and women of S.F. Pd jazz josh
and amy specially the bsu team
for always having our backs
and we're having a bad day.
>> the san francisco sheriff's
department who keeps us safe at
trick sheet the san francisco
fire department our fire radio
officers station 49 our
partners at king and armor
special shout out to chief matt
cannon.
He has been standing beside us
through everything good, bad,
catastrophic fake.
He's brought his own dog ranger
to be our therapy dog when he
can to marion higgins for
keeping us, you know, our
cadillac live the desktop
support and help desk people
that keep us running 24 seven
system watch our union seiu
bert are union officers who
always fight the good fight my
post 48 classes edwin justin
and cindy the entire card
project team who will hopefully
get us by 2027 to a new card
all my friends, my family
and my better half who works
about as much hours as I do.
>> thank you very much.
And finally the award really is
for for leah and last year we
lost flo and from meant a lot
for a minute I was one of her
squad leaders this year we lost
my friend leah 20 years of
proudly serving the city of san
francisco top notch dispatcher
and a force to be reckoned
with.
>> so it's a loss and so I
dedicate this award to her.
>> happy dispatchers.
We thank you.
>> wow.
Thank you, nicole.
That was beautiful.
And most of the people she
thank are also people I would
love to thank and appreciate.
We are all one family and i
want one.
Thank you.
Board of supervisors chairs.
>> thank you supervisor walton
I'm a member of district ten
and I see all that you do.
Thank you.
>> I also like to take a moment
to dedicate all those that
weren't able to make the call
to 911 in time for not always
do they make that call in time
so we have and I want to try to
be there the best that we can
because sometimes we're not
always able to make that call
that that call every second
counts first and foremost I
would love to give our places
to my family who has given me
continuous support without you
in my corner I would not be the
woman that I am today striving
to be the best.
I am deeply honored to be
recognized by my colleagues for
my work as the dispatcher.
We serve as a backbone of the
public safety and a lifeline
for those in need and those
responding to assist our rapid
and precise communication is
crucial in ensuring that
appropriate assistance reaches
those in need promptly from the
first day I began working at
911I took a pledge to maintain
a high standard of service to
our san francisco community to
the fullest extent possible.
>> the reward of aiding others
is profoundly fulfilling.
It is a great honor to serve
the city and county of san
francisco.
I was born and raised in san
francisco and it's even a
greater honor to ensure that
our brothers and sisters in the
fire and police departments
return home safely.
Together we make a significant
difference in our community.
Let us all continue to support
each other and strive for
excellence in service through
the strength and honor.
>> thank you again.
Thank you.
Well, it's all right.
All right, MADAM Clerk, I think
we should go to our 3 P.M.
Special order items 34 through
37 comprise the public hearing
of persons interested in the
determination of exemption from
environmental review under the
california environmental
quality act issued as a
categorical exemption by the
planning department on DECEMBER
18th, 2024 for the proposed
project at 2142 22nd street
which proposes to demolish an
existing single family dwelling
and construct a new six story
building with five new units
five off street parking spaces
housed within stackers and five
bicycle parking spaces.
Item 35 this motion affirms the
determination by the planning
department that the proposed
project is categorically exempt
from environmental review.
Item 36 is the motion that
conditionally reverses the
department's determination that
the project is categorically
exempt from environmental
review subject to the adoption
of the written findings of the
board in support of the
determination and item 37 is
the motion that directs the
preparation of findings.
>> >> all right.
So colleagues, as our clerk has
explained we have before us a
hearing on the appeal of the
determination of exemption from
environmental review for the
proposed project at 2142 22nd
street.
After the hearing the board
will vote on whether to affirm
or conditionally reverse the
categorical exemption
determination for the proposed
project.
I would propose and unless
somebody objects we will
proceed as follows first we
will give up to ten minutes to
the appellant for a
presentation.
Then we will allow public
comment in support of the
appeal two minutes per speaker.
Then we will hear from the
planning department for up to
ten minutes.
Then we will give the project's
sponsor up to ten minutes
and then there will be public
comment in and out in support
of the project sponsor
in opposition to the appeal.
Again, two minutes per speaker.
And finally we'll give the
appellant three minutes for
rebuttal.
Doesn't look like anybody is
objecting to that.
So seeing no objections.
The public hearing will proceed
as indicated and is now open.
>> and I don't see anyone on
the roster but I should ask if
supervisor walton has any
introductory remarks.
>> I will wait to have that.
>> okay, great.
Thank you.
All right.
So let's have the appellant
come forward to present their
case.
>> you have up to ten minutes.
>> good afternoon members of
the board emily bruff for
appellant two one, three, two
and two on three six 22nd
street hoa.
>> can you pull that microphone
close so we can hear you best?
Thank you.
>> but better.
Okay.
Also with me and appearing on
appellant's behalf is
geotechnical and civil engineer
alan kropp who has submitted a
declaration in support of this
appeal and MR. Cropp has also
visited the site at issue
and is who I will turn this
over to in a few minutes to
describe some of the conditions
and factors that appellant has
concerns about here.
So first the issue before the
board today is not whether this
project should be built.
The issue is about whether the
project should receive
environmental review under the
california environmental
quality act ceqa before it is
built.
>> the planning department
determined here that this
project was exempt from
environmental review under
sequa under one of six
enumerated exceptions in the
statute.
>> normally this would be the
case for the typical size of a
proposed residential building
in an urban area.
But when there are unusual
circumstances present and which
raise concerns about potential
significant environmental
impacts, the exemption under
section no longer applies.
>> we believe that is the case
here.
>> first, the project site is
located on a parcel with a
significant a 40% grade
in some areas.
>> second, it is located in an
earthquake landslide zone.
According to california, the
california map the link has
been provided to you in our
briefing.
>> there was an error in the
brief that referred to the zone
as a liquefaction zone.
The project site is and is
in fact an earthquake landslide
zone which is actually even
more unusual in san francisco
than a liquefaction zone is.
And at the same time like a
liquefaction zone poses a
similar risk of permanent
ground displacement.
>> if there is an earthquake.
>> third, in addition to these
two factors, the site has
serpentine bedrock underlying
the surface which is known to
pose the risk of releasing
asbestos fibers into the air
when excavated.
And there's a lot of ground
that is planned here to be
unearthed.
Over 1000yd3 up to
approximately 30ft in depth.
>> the initial project report
has only done borings samples
from the site from depths to 2
to 5ft.
Despite there being planned 30
30ft depths into this
serpentine bedrock, this is
simply inadequate to understand
the site conditions.
>> and as MR. Cropp can explain
further, the projects sponsor
and the planning department
response to this appeal has
pretty much tried to frame
these concerns as common in san
francisco.
And in any event ones that can
be dealt with at a later time
at an unspecified time.
We disagree on several bases.
>> first, secure the unusual
circumstances exception
in sequoia.
>> it's a state wide statute
and courts and view view
circumstances as unusual within
the meaning of sequoia when
quote the circumstances of a
particular project differ from
the general circumstances of
the projects covered by a
particular categorical
exemption.
One here is the size of the
building in an urban area.
>> because this is a state
statute.
We're talking about comparing
the circumstances of the site
here to those similar ones
statewide.
San francisco undoubtedly poses
unusual risks that do not exist
in other statewide residential
projects.
>> but even when just
considering san francisco local
projects, the conditions here
are unusual even for this area.
San francisco, as we know, is a
hilly city and there are
certain certainly projects that
are built on slopes as the
planning department has pointed
out.
But when taking the concerns at
issue here together there is
substantial evidence of unusual
circumstances within the
meaning of sequoia and most
certainly a reasonable
possibility of a significant
environmental impact.
>> due to those circumstances
the significant the state
recognized earthquake land
slides on.
Again unusual even for san
francisco.
And third, the underlying
potentially toxic bedrock.
>> these become the type of
conditions that warrant taking
a closer look at potential
environmental risks.
The factors here shouldn't just
be shrugged off as something
that can be dealt with later at
an unspecified time.
They should be planned for
and in part to prevent damage
to my client's next door
building.
>> the project sponsors on
initial report on this project
recognizes that there are
significant concerns with
respect to my client's next
door foundation and basement.
And all appellant is asking
here is that these concerns be
evaluated at the outset.
That is precisely the function
of what an initial study is
under secure and initial
investigations of the site
conditions that have not been
done adequately at this point.
So that these are known and the
engineers and construction
professionals can be can plan
and be prepared with
appropriate mitigation measures
before construction begins.
>> and with that I'll turn it
over to to MR. Krop and I'm
happy to answer any questions.
>> my name is alan krop.
I've been a practicing
geotechnical engineer in the
bay area for over 50 years.
I have done work for developers
in the city and county of san
francisco and I'm a peer
reviewer for protection act
project submitted to the city.
As I was asked to look at this
project I was quite surprised
by the absence of any certified
engineering geology studies
given the fact that this
material is on serpentine night
which unfortunately is one of
the least stable bedrock types
in the city and county of san
francisco noted for many shear
zones and other problematic
situations.
So when a 30 foot excavation is
to be made it's critical that
the depth of that
material would be characterized
by a geologist for stability.
Unfortunately there have not
been any deep borings at the
site.
There is no geology geologist
identified as having evaluated
the stability of those
materials and that is a concern
both under the protection act
and the seismic hazard map for
earthquake induced landslides
as pointed out as well.
Serpentine site has the second
unfortunate situation that
in certain cases it possesses
asbestos fibers which can be
hazardous during excavation
processes when it introduced
into the air.
So it's my judgment that the
project is not defined at all
with respect to the
geotechnical and geologic
conditions and therefore it is
unknown what the situation will
be.
But all of the other factors
point to a potentially
problematic outcome unless
adequate information can be
developed that would indicate
there is not a risk from
landslides and from asbestos
generation.
>> I'm willing to answer any
questions or go back to emily.
>> that's all we have for our
opening and we're happy to
answer any questions and say a
few words on rebuttal.
>> all right.
Thank you for your
presentation.
I don't see colleagues with
questions for the appellants so
we should open up public
comments for those who'd like
to speak in support of the
appeal and in opposition to the
project.
If there's anyone who wants to
speak during public comment now
line up.
>> uh this is not general
public comment is public
comment.
I'm in support of this
particular appeal.
All right.
It doesn't look to me like
there is so I'm seeing no
speakers in support.
>> public comment is now closed
and then we will hear from the
planning department for up to
ten minutes each.
>> good afternoon PRESIDENT
Mandolin board members my name
is don lewis planning
department staff with me today
are lisa gibson, environmental
review officer and joy
navarette day.
MADAM Clerk, can we please go
to my slides if we go the item
before you is the appeal of a
categorical exemption or cat
acts issued by the planning
department for the two one 4 to
20 second street project
pursuant to the to california
environmental quality act or
sequel our MARCH 11th
department response the appeal
letter is included in the
board's packet as is our
supplemental appeal response
which was submitted on APRIL
11th.
We maintain our position that
the appellant has not met the
legal burden of proof to
successfully challenge the cat
acts and my presentation I will
highlight some of our main
arguments in response to the
appeal and now for a quick
overview of the project.
The project site is located on
the north side of 22nd street
between kansas and rhode island
streets and pitcher hill the
project site is occupied by a
two story single family
residence at the rear of the
lot immediately east uphill is
the appellants building which
is a six story two unit
residential building that was
constructed in 1990.
Immediately west down hill is a
utility right away that runs
along kansas street with no
structures.
>> the project would demolish
the existing residence
and construct a 40 foot tall
six story over basement
residential building with five
dwelling units.
The project would include five
off street parking spaces
housed in stackers and the
proposed building complies with
the planning code school
guidelines established classes
of projects that by definition
are exempt from environmental
review.
The class one cat acts allows
for the demolition of a single
family residence and the class
three cat acts allows for the
construction of up to six
dwelling units.
The project clearly fits within
the class one and three
categorical exemption the
school guidelines also
establish exceptions to the
issuance of a cat x of a cat
issuance of a cat x.
One of these exceptions is
where the project presents an
unusual circumstance that gives
rise to a significant effect.
Another exception is related to
scenic highways none of the
exceptions apply to the
project.
You've heard the appellant's
arguments and I won't repeat
them.
But at a high level our
response is as follows.
Construction on steep slopes is
common in san francisco.
By department estimates
approximately 13% of san
francisco is on slopes of 25%
or greater which works out to
be approximately 39% of parcels
where at least a portion
includes a of 25% or more.
Portions of san francisco are
steep slopes designated as
landslide hazard zones such
such as the project site.
But the location of a project
the size of which has its own
is also not an unusual
circumstance in san francisco.
But even if such a location was
unusual, applicable laws
and regulations would ensure
that construction of the
project would be safe.
San francisco relies on the
state and local regulatory
process for review and approval
of building permits pursuant to
the california building code
and the san francisco building
code.
The project would have no
significant impact related soil
seismic and other geological
hazards.
And I'll just add that project
has a sponsor hasn't even
submitted their building permit
yet.
We have to get through this
process and then they'll begin
that process.
>> excavation of serpentine
bedrock is also common in san
francisco, especially in petri
hill where most parcels are
situated on serpentine bedrock
which contains naturally
occurring asbestos.
But even if such a location was
unusual, the project sponsor
would be required to comply
with the construction dust
control ordinance which would
protect the workers themselves
as well as the public from
fugitive dust that MAY contain
naturally occurring asbestos.
The scenic highway exception
also applies to resources when
the highway officially
designated as a state scenic
highway.
This is one this is exception
that the appellant did raise
in there their appeal letter
but not not not not today but
26 street is not a scenic
highway.
The exception does not apply.
The removal of the holly leave
cherry tree on the project site
will not affect the visual
character of the scenic area as
the project site is not in or
near a scenic sensitive, scenic
or visual area.
In closing, the department has
substantial evidence to support
the determination that the
project qualifies for class one
and three cat x and no
exceptions apply.
The appellant's arguments do
not meet the legal burden of
proof to demonstrate otherwise
and there is no basis for
requiring preparation of a
mitigated negative declaration
or an environmental impact
report.
Therefore we ask that you
uphold the class one and three
cat x and deny the appeal.
That concludes our
presentation.
We are available to answer your
questions.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
>> supervisor walton thank you
so much PRESIDENT Benjamin
and thank you for the
presentation.
I do have one question just
what type of evidence would be
needed for the appellate to
meet the burden of proof that
the project does not meet or
does not qualify for class one
or class three category?
>> sure.
I mean I think everyone agrees
that it fits within a class
wide and class three.
And then in terms of unusual
circumstances it's a two part
test.
>> the first part is is it
unusual?
And if that question is
answered no in the lead agency
planning department with
substantial events and such
shows that it's it's a common
situation, it's not unique then
you don't answer the second
question which is why would it
result in a significant impact?
So based on substantial
evidence based on the slides we
show that there's steep slopes
all over san francisco to tie
and bedrock is pitcher
basically and you know we don't
see that there's anything
unique about the location of
this project.
So the second question we did
address in rapid response for
informational but we don't we
didn't need to because based on
substantial evidence there is
no unusual circumstance.
I hope that answers your
question.
>> all right.
And with that I think we will
go to the project sponsor who
will have up to ten minutes.
>> good afternoon PRESIDENT
Randleman and supervisors.
I'm tonya carolina with robin
junius and rose representing
the project sponsor.
So planning has already
explained why an exemption was
proper here and how the
appellants arguments do not
have any merit.
I'm going to address the second
part in a moment but I also
want to talk a little bit about
what this appeal is really
about.
>> so if we could have the
overhead you going to see an
image of the existing house.
And to the right you see the
appellant next door neighbors
windows on the property line
which are very much relevant to
this appeal.
>> this is not a huge project
but it is an opportunity to
develop a site that's currently
has a small dilapidated 1200
square foot house single unit
house and turned that into five
units including one smaller
approximately 900 square foot
one bedroom unit.
And for approximately 1500 to
1700 square foot three bedroom
homes the project sponsor who's
here today with me hosted
several neighborhood meetings
has been responsive to the
questions including those from
the appellant and has also
modified the project.
>> in response to appellant's
request after the appeal was
filed I reached out to the
appellant's attorney first by
phone call on friday MARCH
14th, about a month ago.
Her and I had a brief
discussion for discussion on
monday MARCH 17th.
Thereafter I followed up a
couple of times by email but
did not really receive any
substantive response including
an email I sent to her on MARCH
26th asking for any follow up
asking specifically to see
mentioning it.
Be helpful to understand your
client's concerns since so far
we have not seen anything
in the board of supervisors
file.
>> I was told that they are
still discussing with the
clients so hopefully follow up
shortly.
I followed up again another
week later asking if there's
any details so that we could
understand if we could
potentially resolve this appeal
outside of the hearing.
And the response I got that
they would be filing their
brief the next day.
>> bottom line we we've
certainly tried to communicate
with the appellant and tried to
see if there's a way to
understand their concerns
and resolve this appeal.
>> our impression is that this
appeal is about two things.
First, for as long as the
appellants have owned the next
door building, they have known
that when our property is
developed they MAY need to
close or protect those property
line windows.
There's a recorded document
that has been on the
appellant's title for over 30
years providing that standard
notice that applies everywhere
in the city to property line
windows.
They have known about it but I
understand and appreciate that
they're not happy to see the
next door property develop
because that does mean that
some of the property line
windows will need to be closed
or protected.
Second, as with any next door
neighbor we understand that the
appellant wants to ensure that
construction of the project is
done responsibly and safely.
>> that is entirely reasonable
but more importantly it's
entirely consistent with what
the project sponsor wants to do
and what the city's well
established building permit
processes provide.
>> filing of a secure appeal is
not the way to address those
concern concerns.
Instead it comes down to the
city's building permit
processes and review
requirements as well as
cooperation and coordination
between neighbors.
>> the project sponsor is happy
to do that.
>> for example, on a very
practical level it would be
helpful for both parties if the
appellant allowed dpr to
release copies of the asset
bill drawings for their
building after this appeal
hearing today.
We will continue to be
available to coordinate with
the appellant and we hope that
they will do that too.
But this today is not the right
venue relative to construction
safety concerns and the
property line windows
themselves have nothing to do
with square really.
So next I want to address the
sequel arguments a little bit
and I know they've already been
covered by planning department
.
The appellant is asking you to
find that the planning the
planning should not have issued
an exemption because unusual
circumstances apply here.
And additionally in their brief
because the scenic resource
exception applies neither is
the case here with respect to
unusual circumstances
exception.
The appellant has the burden to
show as MR. Lewis just stated
that there are unusual
circumstances that distinguish
the project from other projects
and the extent class and then
that there is a fair argument
that the project will have a
significant impact on
environment due to those
unusual circumstances.
>> the appellant's first claim
is that unusual circumstance
applies because the property
has an average in excess of
25%.
That is not an unusual
circumstance in san francisco.
>> on the overhead on the next
slide we see a map that shows
the properties in blue color
in san francisco that have more
than 25%.
This is not unusual and the
appellants property themselves
has a of more than 25%.
>> and in fact the slopes
exceeding 25% are so common
that this board of supervisors
adopted the and seismic hazard
zone protection ordinance which
is codified in our building
code that addresses additional
review and requirements
applicable to building permits
at the site.
I will review the building
permit for this project per
those additional requirements
to ensure that the project will
be safely built.
>> those standard building code
requirements require retention
of a licensed geologist
and licensed technical engineer
who need to prepare certain
reports that are provided to
dpi with the building permit
application.
The appellant claims that we
have failed to comply with that
requirement.
That is not true.
Those reports and all other
requirements are done
in connection with the building
permit application which will
be filed as soon as we have
completed this planning
department process and all of
the requirements that MR. Croft
in noted in appellants remarks
including potential peer review
that happens at the building
permit stage.
>> the appellant also claimed
in their brief that the
property is in the state
liquefaction zone.
I understand that they are no
longer saying that.
On the next slide I had a map
of the state liquefaction zone
which were not in.
They did note that the
properties and the seismic
landslide zone but that is also
covered by the city's building
code by the and seismic hazard
protection zone.
>> lastly, the appellant claims
that the unusual circumstance
applies because the serpentine
bedrock underneath the property
serpentine bedrock is quite
common in san francisco and by
no means does it represent an
unusual circumstance.
On the overhead again on the
next slide I have a map showing
the project site proximity
and there are many nearby sites
with serpentine bedrock shown
in blue.
>> so in summary neither the
site nor the serpentine
bedrock create anything unusual
and certainly nothing that
would suggest creation of a
significant environmental
impact.
If the appellant's concern is
construction safety at this
site given the and serpentine
rock overturning the exception
exemption the appellant is
asking is not the right path.
>> the path forward is to allow
dp and the city to proceed with
the building permit stage.
Using the checklist code
requirements
and well-established review
procedures that apply to hilly
sites.
That same has been done on many
other projects.
in the alternative the
appellant also argued in their
brief that the scenic resource
exception applies to this
project.
On the overhead again on the
next page you see the full text
of that secure exception from
the sql guidelines.
>> in their brief they
conveniently quoted to you only
the part that's highlighted
in blue leaving out the most
important part of that
exception which is in the bold
text which is within a highway
officially designated as a
state scenic highway.
Clearly 22nd street is not a
state scenic highway so this
exception does not apply.
>> so in some it we strongly
believe that there are no
unusual circumstances that
prevent the use of a
categorical exemption.
>> even if you believe that
there were unusual
circumstances.
The city's building code
and other regulations ensure
that construction is completed
safely and therefore there are
no significant environmental
impacts.
And the appellant has also not
indicated that there would be
any impacts.
>> the appellant's own building
next door was built in 1990
and is subject to the same
and serpentine bedrock.
Their building has been there
for over 30 years.
The city's building permit
procedures today are more not
less than they were 30 years
ago.
>> the city today is very well
equipped to handle the building
permit review for this project
and there's absolutely no merit
to the appeal.
We understand that they are not
happy about the closure of the
property line windows which has
not happened in the last 30
years.
But that possibility has been
known for over 30 years per
that recorded notice.
>> so we respectfully ask that
you deny the appeal and allow
this small five unit project to
proceed.
We'd be happy to answer any
questions you MAY have.
>> thank you very much.
Thank you, MISS Catalano.
I don't see any questions so we
will open up public comment
in opposition to the appeal
and in support of the project.
>> if you're here to speak
in support of the project you
should line up and I don't see
anyone so public comments in in
support of the project and in
opposition to the appeal is
closed.
And finally we'll invite the
appellants to present a
rebuttal argument.
You have up to three minutes.
>> thank you.
>> and the project sponsors are
here dedicated a lot of its
time explaining what its
perception of this appeal is
about and sort of addressing
what the actual there are real
concerns here.
The legal standard is whether
unusual circumstances exist at
the project site.
Taken together this 40% grade
is planning pointed out as is
the what the planning pointed
out that a 2,025% or more grade
is is present in 13% I believe
of san francisco's sites.
This is a levels of 40% grade
the serpentine bedrock and the
earthquake landslide zone.
Taken together these pose
unusual circumstances and the
legal standard under this
exception once unusual
circumstances are established
then the party quote only need
to show a reasonable
possibility of a significant
effect due to that unusual
circumstance.
This is not a standard that
there would be an environmental
effect as I think that the
project sponsor quoted.
This is a reasonable
possibility.
We submit that there is
substantial evidence of a
reasonable possibility that a
significant effect would occur
due to these unusual
circumstances presented today.
So with that will submit
and ask that the the appeal be
granted in our favor and the
exemption reversed.
All right then with that.
This public hearing has been
held and is now open and is now
filed and then we will now
consider whether to affirm or
conditionally reverse the
exemption determination for the
proposed project.
>> supervisor walton, thank you
so much PRESIDENT Mando man
and I want to thank both the
appellate and the project
sponsor in planning for
participating in this hearing.
I always wish that neighbors
could really come together
and work together to solve
disputes.
In fact, this is the one part
of the job I wish that we could
be switzerland in.
But because I am a member of
this board in this body I do
have to weigh in and make a
decision when it comes to these
appeals and for that matter I
do not see any evidence to
support the appeal so I vote to
affirm the categorical
exemption determination
and support item 35 and table
items 36 and 37.
>> all right.
Supervisor walton, thank you
for your motion.
It looks like supervisor chan
is seconding that.
MADAM Clerk, will you please
call the roll on the motion to
approve item 35 table 36 and 37
supervisor chan chin eyes
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey eyes
supervisor and audio and go to
you I.
Supervisor fielder fielder I
supervisor mahmood mahmood I
supervisor randleman hi mandell
man I supervisor melgar melgar
I supervisor sutter sutter I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
and supervisor walton walton
either are lebanese all right
without objection item 35 is
approved.
Item 36 and 37 are tabled.
MADAM Clerk this concludes our
3 P.M. Special order and we can
go back to roll call
and colleagues, I'm going to
request that we accommodate our
firefighters who are here for
supervisor sorters introduction
so if we could do supervisor
sorter and then go back to
supervisor chan that would be I
don't think anybody's objected
to that.
>> so supervisor slater, thank
you PRESIDENT Gentlemen
colleagues first is good to be
back.
>> I appreciate all of your
support.
Many of you know that it was a
little over three weeks ago
that my wife and I welcomed our
baby daughter JUNE to san
francisco and it has been a
long 22 days but a happy 22
days.
So I want to thank my
colleagues for your support.
Also my team in our office for
their incredible support.
We district three has a new
constituent.
She is the first neediest
constituent but she is also my
favorite.
>> I want to quickly
acknowledge an introduction
while I was out for two new
entertainment zones in district
three which I'm very excited
about introducing legislation
last week with mayor lurie at
pier 39 and then at union
square for ellis street.
I think these will both be very
successful and I want to thank
all iwd for their support
and partnership in bringing
this forward.
Entertainment zones are proven
tools for economic development
supporting our small
businesses, boosting tourism
and I will be proud to showcase
these to entertainment zones
and hopefully a few more beyond
that and more to come in the
future.
Next and most importantly I
want to introduce in memoriam
and ask that we adjourn our
meeting today in memoriam of a
fallen firefighter from our san
francisco fire department.
To letty up the third age 38
was a valued member of station
three.
He was a seven year member of
the san francisco fire
department.
And to his colleagues he was t
someone to always be counted
upon.
An excellent firefighter and an
incredibly hard worker.
He chose station three because
it is the busiest engine in the
country.
He followed his father into the
department something his father
was always so proud of.
The top family was heavily
involved in the bay area samoan
community and little t as he
was known in his family was
very proud of his samoan
heritage.
He leaves behind his wife naomi
.
I had the chance to visit
station three earlier this year
and station three sits at post
and polk street.
It is consistently one of the
busiest stations in the entire
country.
And in the short half hour that
I was at the station there were
four different call outs.
>> the members at this station
choose it for this exact reason
that it is where you can do the
most good and serve the most
people.
I want to acknowledge the
members of station three who
are present here today.
Fertility I've chosen station
three says a lot about his work
ethic, his character and his
dedication to our city.
He will be missed and I hope
that he and his entire family
know that all of san francisco
is eternally grateful for his
service and his commitment.
>> and the rest I submit.
Thank you supervisor sartor.
Thank you for your attendance
here this afternoon.
Thank you for your service.
>> supervisor.
>> I, I wanted to also send my
deepest condolences to the
family, friends and colleagues
of tyler.
I know he was an incredible
valued member of station three
which serves the residents of
the tenderloin and when I
received the call from chief
chris bean that he's lost it
hit me in many different ways
especially just knowing how
young he was.
It's my 30th birthday tomorrow
and hearing that he was the
exact same age made me really
it resonated a lot with our
generation and so I count
fathom though the unfathomable
loss for his family
and throughout the firefighter
community and your station I
know his service to our
residents was deeply
appreciated and I just want you
to know that his memory be a
blessing.
>> so thank you.
Supervisor mahmood supervisor
walton it's suggested that we
have this in memoriam be from
the whole board and that seems
to me like a good idea.
So we'll do that without
objection.
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
And then moving to the top of
the list, supervisor chin.
>> colleagues, today it's my
great pleasure to introduce our
resolution adding the
commemorative street name of
jerry garcia street to heron
ten between alemany boulevard
and mission street.
>> this commemorative street
naming is an opportunity to
recognize the many
contributions that musical
legend and a district 11 native
jerry garcia has made to our
city.
>> these are living contribute
against which our communities
still benefit from today.
>> we all know that jerry
garcia as a co-founder and a
musician after wall famous band
the grateful dead's but his
impact goes far beyond.
>> he was a community advocate
,a vocal supporter of
environmental justice and also
spent his career working to
eliminating barriers to music.
Jerry's vision for community
accessing to music was the most
notable present of his advocacy
for cancers in the past and the
transformation of the grateful
dead's communal home on ashbury
street into a space dedicated
to free music.
>> his memory still brings
people from all the bay area
together through through
through the jerry day
celebrations that took place
annually at mclaren park.
>> in the jerry garcia empathy
empathy others as and as the
district 11 residents I am so
incredibly proud to see that
our district continues to
reflect many of the values that
he represent at it free
and accessible music musical
opportunity especially for our
young people.
The power of community
organizing and a sense of san
francisco and especially
elliott district 11 pray.
>> I also want to thank the
community members who have been
involved in this process and I
especially want to thank
jerry's family for their
support.
And I also have a second one
today.
I also want to introduce our
resolution in support of
california state assembly bill
611 the kip news independent
act introduced by assembly
member alex lee.
>> we have all witnessed
firsthand the nexus the
necessity of having local
independent and accessible news
outlets that our community
members can trust with the
amount of information available
to the public.
>> and it's important that we
stand on the side of
transparency, truth
and community.
In my very own district I know
that our seniors relies heavily
on their community newspaper
not just for news or city
updates but for critical
information regarding their
access to health care,
transportation, food safety
and direct services that they
rely on.
But we are living in an era
where misinformation spreads
quickly and only becoming more
and more difficult to come back
.
>> ab six ab six one one helps
us fight disinformation by
ensuring that local journalism
doesn't quietly get bought up
by cooperation with no ties to
our communities.
>> when local reporters lose
their jobs or when editorial
decisions are made by corporate
chains out of state, we lose
the very people who can tell
our stories which operates what
accuracy and care.
>> this bill doesn't block
sales it's simply just say that
if a legacy news outlet it's
going to be sold to a big
corporation the community
deserves to know.
>> ab 611 gifts us gifts our
communities a chance to explore
alternatives and it sends a
clear message that californians
believe in public
accountability not just
in government but in the
institution that inform us.
>> this is a practical,
thoughtful bill that helps to
restore power to communities
workers and readers.
>> it supports democracy,
public trust and the free flow
of accurate information.
>> I'm grateful to california
common cause and the local
independent publisher in san
francisco for spearheading this
important effort and the rest I
will submit.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
Supervisor chen supervisor
dorsey submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor and engardio submit
.
Thank you.
Supervisor fielder thank you.
Colleagues today I have a few
items and so in advance I thank
you for your patience.
>> first off I would like to
recognize an organization
that's made a big difference
in the lives of so many.
>> both people and animals the
san francisco spca founded on
APRIL 18th, 1868, the spca is
not only one of the oldest
animal welfare organizations
in the nation but also one of
the most impactful from
launching the very first horse
ambulance in 1884 to pioneering
the no kill movement in 1994.
The S.F. Spca has consistently
been ahead of its time
redefining what's possible
in the world of animal welfare.
>> their work is not just about
saving animals.
It's about strengthening the
fabric of our community.
In 2024 alone the S.F. Spca
helped keep over 20,000 beloved
pets with their families
through free mobile vaccine
clinics, community veterinary
care and financial assistance.
>> their hospital provided over
30,000 visits making high
quality affordable health care
accessible to thousands of san
franciscans including myself
and my pet cat pepper.
>> and just last year their
tireless advocacy helped launch
adopt a pet day across
california finding loving homes
for more than 3600 animals.
Today we honor not just their
historic legacy but their
continued commitment to
creating a more compassionate
future.
And so it is with great pride
that I introduced a resolution
proclaiming APRIL 18th, 2025 as
san francisco spca day.
>> thank you to supervisors
chen walton sauder, melgar
mahmud and cheryl for being
early co-sponsors on this
resolution.
>> and moving on I am today
unfortunately compelled to
introduce an ordinance to
protect a child's right to
shelter by preventing city
funded shelters from kicking
families with children out of
shelter within 12 months unless
providers are able to find
those families viable housing.
>> I believe and I think you
all here would agree that no
child should ever worry about
where they will sleep at night.
>> we as a city should be
working around the clock to end
family homelessness not
punishing families for our own
failures to provide viable
exits to affordable housing.
As you know, in DECEMBER of
2020 for the department of
homelessness and supportive
housing imposed a 90 days stay
limit on families living
in shelters with up to 330 day
extensions at the discretion
and of shelter providers
and further 30 day extensions
at the discretion of h.
>> s h.
As stated, intent of the policy
was to create flow through the
family shelter system which has
a waitlists of more than 200
families.
>> the policy itself did not
provide solutions to resolve
long standing systemic flows
which agency h has acknowledged
any flow that has happened is
likely due to the successive
rollout of rapid rehousing
slots and hotel vouchers that
have been coming online from
the $50 million package that
accompanied these reforms from
the former administration.
>> and these extra slots are
still not enough to house all
of our unhoused families.
Along with a lack of access to
homelessness.
There are persistent problems
with coordinated entry
and access points.
A severe shortage of fairly
compensated case managers.
A shortage of multilingual case
managers.
High turnover of case managers
and most of all a severe lack
of new family specific shelter
beds.
>> permanent supportive housing
and affordable housing exits.
>> my goal with this
legislation is to prevent
agencies and shelter providers
from removing families from
shelter before 12 months if
there is no successful option
for housing.
Why?
Because for many of the
families in shelter right now
facing unique barriers to
exiting homelessness, they need
more than 3090 days to resolve
those challenges.
>> this policy is causing
unnecessary fear and trauma
with revolving 30 day
extensions that MAY or MAY not
be granted based on a family's
case manager or family
provider.
>> we want to stop the circular
eviction threats and last
minute extensions that have
caused so much
counterproductive pain
and anxiety for families
and children and instead work
on solutions for housing
and exits from family
homelessness agency.
>> and the providers MAY say
that this policy will leave
them hamstrung and forced to
house people for one year.
That is a mischaracterization
of this policy.
>> if a family has an exit to
homelessness in less than one
year that's great.
The city should work round the
clock to make that happen and I
will work with angel sage
and the mayor's office and all
of you to do so.
San francisco is one of the
wealthiest cities in the world.
Family homelessness is not an
issue of a lack of resources
but rather of political will.
>> thank you to supervisors
chan, chen watson and melgar
for your earlier co-sponsorship
.
And city attorneys adam radtke
and anne pierson and my
legislative aid jen for account
for your work on this measure.
>> I hope that all of you will
sign on to protect a child's
right to shelter.
>> and finally today I'd like
to offer an in memoriam
in honor of lee curtis of
randolph, vermont, a district
nine resident, an avid athlete
and skier and an employee of
the california public utilities
commission.
>> elliot tragically passed
away on APRIL 5th at the far
too young age of 26.
>> ellie moved to san francisco
two years ago after graduating
from dartmouth where she was an
ncaa all-american and captain
of her alpine ski team.
A member of the divest
dartmouth and the
sustainability chair of her
professional fraternity kappa
delta epsilon.
>> as an athlete, ellie was
dedicated to being the best
skier she could be
and demonstrated this by
constantly pushing her own
limits.
>> her coach at dartmouth said
that she was fearless and one
of the hardest workers he had
seen in as many years of
coaching and this applied to
her many pursuits outside of
skiing.
>> a government
and environmental policy major.
Ellie's passion for protecting
the environment and the natural
beauty of our outdoors
naturally extended to her
academic pursuits of the
intersectionality between our
energy, economic and social
justice systems.
After graduating from college,
ellie moved to san francisco
where she took a job as a
regulatory analyst at the cpc.
>> she is excited to put her
degree and her passion for
social justice to work for the
public interest, building
equitable pathways to clean
and sustainable energy.
>> in her own words by marrying
the challenges of
decarbonization with structural
inequality, I'm hopeful that
the energy transition will
force us to rebuild our
conceptions of justice in the
same way that it will force us
to rebuild our built
environment.
>> I met ellie last year when
she volunteered at my campaign
and found her to be warm, kind
and passionate about both
environmental advocacy and her
commitment to social justice.
>> volunteering her time with
local nonprofits and in the
service of others gave ellie
hope even as she was concerned
by the natural situation
and the future of our country.
Inspired her to go deeper into
the work of caring for others
in a land we get to live on.
>> this was ellie in a
nutshell.
>> driven never one to despair
and a source of encouragement
to those around her.
I'm so proud to have been
supported by a person like
allie and equally saddened by
the tragedy that took her life
at such a young age.
Before we were able to see the
great things she would no doubt
accomplish.
The possibilities will be
endless and heartbreaking.
>> ellie's family wishes for
you to hold ellie in your
hearts as she transitions to a
new place among the stars.
Wind mountains spring runoff
and mycelium.
>> she will be all around us
all the time.
>> always and forever.
I want to extend my deepest
condolences to his parents,
carrie and catch her sister
lainey and the rest of her
friends and family.
>> rest in peace and power out
curse.
>> thank you.
Supervisor fielder supervisor
mahmood.
>> colleagues today I'd like to
introduce a resolution and that
is unfortunately very timely.
>> just a few moments ago I was
joined by labor groups like
seiu 87 and ifp local 21
immigrant rights groups like
iraq and and care.
City hall colleagues and for
many of you in the board of
supervisors as to the director
of the office of civic
engagement and immigrant
affairs to our assessor
recorder representatives of the
san francisco democratic party
and immigrant rights activists
from across the city who
gathered today to send a clear
message in this city we do not
tolerate threats on our
residents and we stand together
always to protect the privacy
and human rights of our
immigrant community.
>> I'm grateful to each of you
who participated in the
demonstration of our collective
power because last week when we
heard the reports emerged the
irs had entered into an
agreement to share data on
undocumented immigrants with
ice.
I thought of the arab and the
muslim and latino immigrants
families in the tenderloin, the
ethiopian immigrant community
in the fillmore in countless
communities throughout our city
who work day in, day out to
live out the american dream.
>> I think of my own family who
immigrate to this country over
40 years ago to live out that
very same promise of the
american dream a dream that is
threatened daily by the actions
taken by our federal
government.
>> we've seen these targeted
attacks before during the first
term of administration we saw a
muslim ban that made so many
in our community lose their
sense of safety.
And we hear ice deportation
threats spread fear in our
communities.
Now our hardworking taxpaying
residents are being put at risk
for contributing to the
economic prosperity and social
fabric of our country.
tax days is usually a
fastidious day but today it's
become an opportune day for
this federal government to
stoke fear in immigrant
community and erode trust
in the people in our
institutions.
>> as a city we have to be
clear that these actions by the
federal government do not
represent us.
And on this tax day we stand
with our heart, our heads held
high, unified in support of the
children in the families
and the seniors and immigrant
community.
>> that is why today I'm
introducing a resolution
in today's chambers to reaffirm
our city's non-cooperation with
identity based registry
ordinance to uphold our
constitutional rights and to
show san francisco will
continue to oppose the federal
government's infringement on
our civil rights.
>> this ordinance was created
under late mayor ed lee in 2017
to protect our residents under
the threat for a muslim ban
during the first trump
administration.
>> back then san francisco made
it clear by enacting chapter
103 of the administrative code
the noncooperation with
identity based registry
ordinance that it will not
support, assist or cooperate
with any governmental program
designed to create, implement
or enforce religious or ethnic
registry or database.
If the federal government
attempts to create databases or
registries to target
individuals based on religion,
ethnicity or national origin,
the city will continue to
uphold its responsibility to
protect its residents from
these discriminatory practices
by complying with the
requirements of chapter 103
that limit disclosure of
personal information for these
purposes.
If federal authorities attempt
to implement registries based
on religion, ethnicity or
national origin.
San francisco will continue to
stand united with its residents
and opposition to efforts to
target, harass or subject
individuals to prejudice based
on their religious affiliation,
ethnicity or national origin.
>> this resolution reaffirms
the city and county of san
francisco's commitment to
religious freedom tolerance
and diversity and rejects any
proposal to create or support
any government registry or
database based on religious
affiliation or national origin
or ethnicity.
>> it's been endorsed by iraq
mission action and the african
advocacy network and I'm
thankful for the support of the
immigrant rights groups as well
as to many of our board
colleagues.
Supervisor fielder melgar.
Dorsey walton.
Cheryl mendelson chen and so
der
for their early co-sponsorship.
I'd like to thank our city
attorney brad rossi for his
support and my team for helping
draft this resolution.
Because democracy thrives
in diversity and it thrives on
community and I can think of no
better city where this rings
true.
Our city has always been a
beacon of hope and in these
stormy times we must continue
to let the light of people
illuminate our future with the
democratic values that we have
always guided us through dark
times.
And so to the immigrants of our
city this is to tell them that
we see you.
We stand with you and will
continue to fight for you today
and always.
And so colleagues, I urge you
to support this resolution
in the weeks ahead.
>> so the rest I submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor mahmood supervisor
mendelsohn thank you, MADAM
Clerk.
I have a few things today a
couple of resolutions, an
ordinance and an in memoriam.
>> the first resolution is
in support of assembly bill
1363 whalen's law introduced by
assembly member catherine
stefani.
This legislation adds reporting
and accountability requirements
around protective orders
in california to protect
children and families from the
harmful impacts of gun violence
as the federal government has
failed to address the evils of
gun violence in america it has
been and is all the more
important for state and local
governments to enact common
sense gun safety laws to keep
children and families safe.
Assemblywoman stephanie champ
championed many of these
efforts in her time on the san
francisco board of supervisors
including introducing
resolutions to impose taxes on
firearms and enforce proactive
trauma responses to victims of
gun violence.
>> but the work is plainly
unfinished as stories like
violence so tragically
demonstrate.
In DECEMBER 2016 the kings
county superior court issued a
nine month restraining order
with a firearm prohibition
against victor gomez after he
threatened to kill his son
while in thomas comes less than
nine months after the issuance
of the protective order.
>> the department of justice
approved gomez's application
for a firearm despite the
explicit firearm prohibition.
>> gomez would later fire the
doj approved gun at wyland
before turning it on himself.
>> after island's mother kristi
camara filed multiple public
records requests to the
department of justice, she
discovered inconsistencies
in data entries and a failure
to enforce the restraining
orders.
>> firearm prohibition.
The california department of
justice subsequently denied
camera's request for
information about the firearm
sold to her ex-husband after
two years of legal battles.
>> the san francisco superior
court ordered the disclosure of
records revealing that the
kings county superior court
failed to transmit three of
four restraining orders against
gomes through the proper
channels, including the one
with the firearm prohibition.
This system failure allowed
whalen's father to obtain the
gun that would eventually kill
weiland.
Whalen's law amend section
18170 of the penal code by
requiring superior courts
and the doj to maintain records
of acquisition and transmission
of protective orders
and requiring prompt disclosure
of such records to a
petitioner.
Respondent protected person or
their representative.
Ab 1363 requires all superior
courts and the department of
justice to create and post an
electronic form and email
address to facilitate
electronic requests for records
on their respective websites.
Under the heading violence law
record request I hope you will
join me in supporting this
in supporting whalen's law to
foster greater transparency
and accountability in our
ongoing efforts to create safer
communities.
And I want to thank supervisors
mahmood walton and cheryl for
their co-sponsorship of this
resolution.
>> secondly, colleagues, you
MAY recall that a few weeks ago
as he sometimes does.
Reverend amos brown spoke
in this chamber and in this
case he was talking to us about
the elimination of his mentor,
civil rights activist
and martyr medgar evers.
From federal websites as part
of the federal administration's
efforts to remove any online
resources that they deem
related to diversity equity
and inclusion.
Reverend brown, we heard you
and we agree.
and today supervisor walton
and I are introducing a
resolution to put this board on
record in formal opposition to
these misguided and destructive
efforts and to highlight the
contributions of medgar evers
in JANUARY the PRESIDENT Issued
two executive orders that call
for the termination of the
mandates policies, programs,
preferences and activities
in the federal government.
Shortly thereafter many
websites associated with the
department of defense began
purging photos and posts that
referenced women bipoc
and lgbtq plus service members
in order to determine what to
delete.
Officials used ai to look for
any content with words such as
gay woman and black among
others.
This resulted in a number of
pages including one referencing
medgar evers being flagged for
deletion.
Evers a black world war two vet
the city's first field
secretary in mississippi and a
father and husband was
returning home after a meeting
of the naacp on JUNE 12th, 1963
when he was shot and killed by
a unknown white supremacist
white supremacist on the steps
of his front porch.
While his death was brutal
and senseless.
It was not in vain.
Effort evers efforts during his
lifetime to advance the full
equal rights of black people
helped lead to the passage of
the civil rights act the
following year.
The resolution calls on the
administration to end the
erasure of great americans like
medgar evers and reaffirms our
city's commitment to providing
a diverse, equitable, inclusive
and belonging environment for
all who live, work and visit
san francisco.
I want to thank reverend brown
for bringing this issue to our
attention and I want to thank
calvin and melanie mathewson
in my office for their work on
the resolution.
>> next I'm introducing an
ordinance to expand the
boundaries of the castro lgbtq
cultural district to include
the dubious triangle
neighborhood to boast triangle
is adjacent to the castro
in both proximity and history.
After the 1969 summer of love,
lgbtq people began moving from
the hate to the castro
and eureka valley.
>> the and lesbians
transformed the victorians
in the triangle and developed a
community that continues to
this day.
Before harvey milk moved to
and set up his camera store on
castro street in 1972 he lived
at 24 henry street in tebow's
both triangle the first lesbian
biker bar scott in san
francisco.
Scott's pit was located on at
ten sanchez street and tebow's
triangle from 1970 to 1984
and many other lgbtq businesses
have been located in the
neighborhood since then,
including the tebow's triangle
neighborhood in the castro
lgbtq cultural district would
be an acknowledgment of its
rich shared history with the
castro.
Legislation has the support of
the tebow's triangle
neighborhood association and I
want to thank my former aide
adam talks about my current aid
on huh and deputy city attorney
brad ritchie for their work on
the ordinance.
And finally I'm asking that we
adjourn adjourn today's meeting
in memory of scott nielsen who
died from natural causes on
MARCH 14th.
Scott received his bachelor of
science in finance from boston
university.
He worked for more than a
decade as an auditor in the
insurance industry and dabbled
as a field technician.
He earned his master's
in public administration from
san francisco state in 2009
and thereafter shifted his
career focus towards the
nonprofit sector and the arts.
In 2014, scott began his
nonprofit work as an intern for
intersection for the arts, an
organization dedicated to
helping artists grow through
fiscal sponsorships
and professional development
programs.
He worked as the director of
finance and administration with
the stanford jazz workshop
and huckleberry youth programs
but returned to intersection
for the arts as a board member
in 2017 and accepted the role
of director of finance in 2019.
He led the annual budget
and financial planning process
in addition to managing the
audit process and banking
relationships and more broadly
working to support the
financial health of the
organization and helping staff
and board members with more
than 140 fiscally sponsored
projects beginning in 2013.
Scott was a valued member of
the A.P. Toklas lgbt democratic
club and served as the club's
treasurer and co-chair co-chair
of its field committee.
Former alice co-chairs gina
sweeney and eric luke lucas
described him as always humble.
He never sought the limelight
but exuded true leadership.
He never failed to do what was
right or tell others what he
knew to be right.
His passing too soon leaves us
with a painful hole in our
hearts and we will dearly MISS
His gentle demeanor, infectious
laugh and lasting friendship.
Rest in peace and power, scott.
MAY or MAY your memory be a
blessing.
And the rest I submit.
>> thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor melgar.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
>> and I have a couple of
things.
Colleagues this week marks the
anniversary of san francisco's
1906 earthquake on APRIL 18th
one hundred and 19 years ago.
The 7.9 magnitude earthquake
and the firestorm that followed
killed 3000 people and left
250,000 others homeless.
On that day the brick walls of
our old city hall crumbled
in seconds despite the building
itself having only been open
for ten years.
It was destroyed except for the
steel structure of the dome
nearby though on 13th
and mission nearly another
early san francisco building
stood strong.
The humble beacon's van
and storage warehouse this
warehouse still stands today
largely because it was a
pioneer for its time being one
of the first buildings in the
entire state of california to
use concrete reinforced with
steel.
The 1906 earthquake
demonstrated to the world that
resilient fireproof materials
and high standards make a
difference.
>> however, as our written
building code in retrofit
technologies have evolved over
time, our city still has some
concrete buildings in our midst
that MAY be vulnerable to the
next big one.
So tomorrow colleagues I will
be presenting legislation to
improve the seismic safety of
the city's concrete buildings
at the building inspection
commission.
This legislation was developed
with the city administrator's
office and by experts to help
us understand and map out which
buildings MAY be vulnerable to
earthquakes.
It will give owners who are
ready to retrofit to clear
building codes standards at
which they have been lacking so
that they do not have to redo
the work while making their
self their building safer.
>> today I am also introducing
along with PRESIDENT Mandell
men supervisor cheryl dorsey
and field for a resolution
commemorating the 110th
anniversary of the armenian
genocide and declaring APRIL
24th, 2025 as the armenian
genocide commemoration day
in the city and county of san
francisco.
The armenian genocide is one of
the most atrocious crimes
against humanity resort
resulting in the murder of over
1.5 million armenians by the
turkish empire.
Yet to this day there continues
to be an official policy of
denialism by the governments of
turkey and azerbaijan a
denialism that is only more
emboldened by extremists so
hate and division in our
communities and the occupation
of our talk and armenia's
territories by the government
of azerbaijan since 2022.
>> the armenian community is
still feeling threatened in san
francisco and all over the
world in recent years here
in san francisco.
There were shots fired at the
kcb armenian school in my
district.
An arson that took place at st
gregory's armenian church
and supervisor cheryl's
district that also housed a
community center which has not
yet been fully repaired to the
cross at the top of mt.
Davidson is constantly defaced
with hateful graffiti.
>> our places of worship at
refuge should not be places of
fear.
We must condemn these acts.
>> that is why we need to
constantly remind ourselves
that we cannot combat hate
without first acknowledge our
past that defending human
rights is not only a global
issue but one that impacts us
locally too.
This resolution also urges that
we continue to educate students
about the armenian genocide as
part of our school curriculum.
I want to thank the armenian
national committee of america
bay area chapter for their
advocacy and acknowledge the
resilience of the armenian
people in district seven in san
francisco here and around the
world.
The rest I submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor melgar.
Supervisor cheryl colleagues I
want to echo my support
and echo brother PRESIDENT
Mandell in supporting assembly
members assembly members
stephanie's violins what law?
>> there is no doubt that we
have little support
in preventing gun violence at
the federal level today but the
reality is there is still much
we can do here in california
and in san francisco.
Public safety is of course
about a fully staffed police
department but it is also about
ensuring that we have systems
in place to protect at risk
communities systems like
islands, law systems like the
mayor's office of victims
and witness rights and systems
like safe storage facilities.
>> I commend assembly member
stephanie in driving our public
safety apparatus forward not
just on the obvious things but
also on the things that will
save lives every day.
>> the rest I submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor sheryl supervisor
walton thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues today along with
supervisors melgar chan
and chen I'm introducing a
resolution declaring APRIL 11th
through APRIL 17th, 2025 as
black maternal health week here
in san francisco.
in addition, I'm calling for a
hearing on black maternal
health.
This national week of awareness
was officially recognized by
the white house in 2021
and APRIL 11th also marks the
international day for maternal
health and rights here in san
francisco.
The data is clear and it is
deeply disturbing.
While black birthing mothers
make up just 4% of total births
,they account for 50% of
pregnancy related deaths.
Preterm birth has worsened for
black women more than any other
racial group since before the
pandemic in 2020.
And that of course is absolute
unacceptable.
>> we also know that 45% of
black birthing mothers in our
city live below the federal
poverty line.
The leading causes of maternal
death, embolism, infection
and chronic conditions like
cancer and hypertension are
tied to broader systems of
inequity including economic
instability, environmental
stress, racial bias
and barriers to care.
These disparities are rooted
in systemic racism, but we also
know it is a solvable problem.
There are community driven
programs that are already
making a difference here in san
francisco and we must continue
our city's commitment to
investing in and protecting the
lives of all birthing people
especially by uplifting the
health, well-being and joy of
black birthing mothers here
in san francisco.
The rest I submit.
>> thank you supervisor walton
seeing no names on the roster.
>> that concludes the
introduction of new business.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Let's go to public comment.
>> all right.
Now it's time for you all to
line up on your right hand side
of the chamber.
We're setting the timer for two
minutes.
You're ready for the drill.
You know you can speak to the
mayor's presentation.
You can speak to the minutes.
You can speak to items
generally but just not on any
items that are on our agenda.
>> all right.
Welcome, chris.
Good afternoon.
Board of supervisors early
richard.
For the record, my name is
christopher klein.
I also go by sergeant klein,
the united states marine corps.
Earlier today a town in the
caribbean approved that war
funds.
And earlier I've spoken about
our troops being in the
caribbean.
And there's trouble trouble
looming.
>> late last week at the human
rights council that was
canceled because we didn't have
enough people show up.
I wanted to present a few
things here in san francisco
that were very concerning.
I urged the board of
supervisors and the PRESIDENT
Of the board of supervisors to
immediately convene a justice
council meeting
and specifically concerning
frequencies that are not to be
used for specifically for
things that are emergencies
and those are being used
outside of san francisco as
well.
So I've already spoke with I
have sent emails to the
sheriff, the police chief
and other individuals.
Again, immediately convene a
justice council meeting to
discuss this.
They should be held every three
months.
They haven't been.
Other than that, pray for peace
and pray for everyone's safe
return.
Hopefully there's not war
in the caribbean like 1983.
And I'd like to take a moment
of silence for all the people
lost in san francisco
and elsewhere because of this
violence and nonsense.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Welcome to our next speaker.
MR. Brown, I I'm just here to
talk about my son.
>> I've been coming here for
the last 19 years about
unsolved homicides.
>> and there's supposed to be
there was a resolution passed
by the police commission to pay
tipsters to come forward with
information and that they won't
be penalized and they will be
safe.
>> I am still waiting for you
know, the there's a new
district, a D.A. That is
supposed to help implement
this, you know, with matt
darcy.
>> and I'm still waiting that I
thought it was supposed to
happen soon.
>> I'm excited that this is
happening.
I know things are going to be
changed and they're supposed to
talk with the cindy lot of the
police commission.
But but why are we why what are
we waiting for?
>> killings are still you guys
got to talking about gun
violence and all these things
and people are getting killed.
>> why do we have to wait for
something to be implemented for
tipsters to come forth?
>> we talk about people buying
guns and all this but no one's
saying anything if you give
them incentive and paying them
to to come forth they will.
We talk about the snitch
culture.
Nobody wants to say anything.
>> if you give them an
incentive to say something they
will.
>> I am definitely waiting on
this this new D.A. To help
implement this.
I'm not knowing who she is but
I'm praying that there's
supposed to be one thing
changed on there.
You know the D.A. Is not going
to be involved the police.
It's going to be up to the
police chief to to to do this.
So if the D.A. Is involved is
going to take longer.
But hopefully this will come
forth really soon.
This month I'm hoping that this
new that this happens.
Matt darcy, please.
>> I am so waiting and mothers
like myself are so waiting for
this to happen.
>> thank you, MS..
Brown.
Just a reminder to address your
comments to the board as well.
i don't know what else to do.
>> I've been waiting for a
long.
Thank you so much.
All right, let's welcome our
next speaker please.
>> good afternoon.
I am virginia marshall, a
retired educator.
>> however, there are a group
of us here today representing
major blunt to MR. PRESIDENT
board of supervisors to our
favorite son of san francisco
and the african-american
community supervisor walter
that we love you dearly
and thank you for all your hard
work.
>> however, we have some
concerns about mega black
and as a committee we each have
a part to share.
>> come quickly committee
members.
>> I'll reserve the rest of my
minute to come back.
We have a letter to go to each
of you and to the clerk.
Thank you.
We'll come collect that from
you.
>> thank you for your comments
.
>> hello and thank you for
listening.
This is addressed to the
mayor to the board of
supervisors and to the human
rights commission.
This is my first time speaking.
I'm excited to be here.
I grew up in san francisco.
I'm a daughter of granddaughter
of san francisco.
I'm a former news reporter,
executive producer, crown for
television kpbs iheartmedia
westwood one kqed total traffic
and weather network.
i've done a lot in media.
And then I created clarity
media my own nonprofit media
organization founded by the
dream keeper initiative.
And it is my honor to represent
mega black and the many
organizations and community
members who have benefited
and celebrated the dream keeper
initiative and all of the
successes that we have had.
Let's talk about the successes.
And we would like to extend our
heartfelt gratitude to all of
you for your commitment to
uplifting the black community
in san francisco.
The investments made through
the dream keeper initiative
have been transformative
providing essential resources
that have strengthened families
,empowered individuals
and laid the foundation for
long term economic and social
stability.
And as a ceo and founder of my
media organization, it is my
responsibility to be objective
and truth seeking.
And I ask the question where is
the rest of the dki funding?
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Welcome our next speaker.
Welcome.
>> how are you doing?
My name is jeffrey greer
and tonight this afternoon I'm
representing mega black.
Initially the dream keeper
initiative was funded annually
with a $60 million investment
in 2000.
>> in 2024 the amount was
reduced to 45 million annually
and the dollars released in a
request for proposals.
>> the total amount grant the
total amount grant is listed as
less than $20 million as it is
today per year spread across
three different areas.
And after numerous community
meetings engagements with the
mayor's office, the human
rights commission we were not
informed about this monumental
cut to the funding.
>> to quote recent comments it
is designed genuis to suggest
that the administration is
centering the black community
while quietly reducing the
allocated funds from the last
two years from 90 million to
$19 million.
>> that's just an excerpt of
the letter you all will receive
so that you can receive it all
in context.
But as an individual I've
witnessed the changes that have
taken place in san francisco as
a result of this monumental
funding.
>> san francisco should be
holding this up as a pinnacle.
They should be.
They should be advertising this
and speaking to the entire
nation about the success of
this mission.
>> instead, as a people that
are facing extinction, we are
trying to defend the fact that
we even exist.
So you need to take another
look at it.
We've already given our 10% to
help the city reduce the
budget.
So perhaps you can feed the
people.
>> thank you.
Thank you, MR. Greer, for your
comments.
>> welcome to the next speaker.
Yes, my name is larry martin.
i'm also a member of mega black
.
And I'm going to read the third
paragraph in this letter
in your announced minute for
the request for proposals you
use a misleading table with
derogatory, disparaging
and negative language.
And by the way, this is
directed to the board of
supervisors to describe the
difference between that we this
request and previous request
for funding the dream keeper
initiative in your quest to
malign the previous
administration.
You also devalue the successes
of the dream keeper initiative
,the black community
and organizations who invested
countless hours into advancing
the work.
And I just want to say that,
you know, it would be the best
interests of you board of
supervisors to reallocate the
$90 million that was allocated
for the black community.
Yeah.
Talk about gun violence
and stuff like that.
This money was doing doing
positive things for black
organizations in the black
community to take that away.
It's like putting a gun in one
of the youngster's hand, you
know what I'm saying?
So it would be in the best
interest to reallocate the
money because it's important he
was doing something positive
in the black community, in the
black organizations.
So to take that away would be
like a slap in the face
in adopting the racist policies
that's coming from the federal
government is trying to trickle
down to the san francisco.
So it would it would be in the
best interest to allocate the
money in and say no to the
racist policies that so many of
your some of your that might
want to like or that you don't
see and so just think about
that.
Think about that because
there's consequences.
>> thank you for your comments.
Let's hear from our next
speaker.
Please welcome.
>> hi.
My name is levi shepherd.
I just want to say in 2021 I
was hit by a car in the mission
and that's what landed me here.
I was paralyzed.
And today I'm actually getting
back to mobility.
This dream keeper initiative
actually allowed me the
opportunity to be able to get
my education.
We received funding and there
was scholarships that we
received actually to work on
our master's degrees through
usf.
But what I want to share with
you is that as the last
paragraph there, it is
troubling how this
administration continues to
speak of accountability
and transparency but only point
to your perceived notions of
failure and the dream keeper
initiative with little
acknowledgment of the program's
success, measurable outcomes
and the overwhelmingly positive
perception from the community
including a 95% approval rating
their reported data on the
amount of harm on earth is off
by 75%.
>> there's no mention of the
number of students supported
in pursuing higher education
and a substantial impact on
behavioral health services
provided through the initiative
should be celebrated.
>> um we kind of tired of also
just coming down and it kind of
feel like a bag of something.
>> this is money that is due to
us and that's due to our
community and we're actually
demanding that it gets refunded
back to the community.
>> so whatever meeting you need
to have talking to you need to
have whatever you need to do to
make it happen.
>> we need to get those
findings back to the hands of
the community where they
belong.
>> again, my name is lieber
shepherd.
>> thank you for your comments.
>> I think I have one minute
left from my time.
The van sorry the vision came.
Ma'am, can you hold on one
second?
You you walked away from the
podium with the with about a
minute but I'll typically we do
not hold on one moment please.
Typically we do not allow
people who've walked away from
the podium to return to the
podium and continue with their
public comment.
And I'm just sharing that with
you for next time conduct your
public comment taking the full
two minutes but because you
have important matters to share
with us today, I will set the
timer for one minute and let
you proceed.
>> this is the people's house
and I'm not too.
Thank you so much.
I won't.
>> I want to first want to
thank you.
You MAY begin for a vision.
DR. Cheryl davis DR. Sayeeda
looked at the t for burch
and supervisor walton for
getting us here today.
I request is simple that each
of you who represent a district
in san francisco that you will
fully fund the dream keepers
initiative it has helped more
than 30 cbos across this city
from pete from pre-k to
adulthood and doing so many
positive things.
We invite you to come to our
thursday meetings.
>> thank you so much and again
I am not too that was very
disrespectful.
>> thank you and I would not
tolerate it.
You have to.
>> four seconds left, ma'am.
All right.
Thank you for your comments.
Let's hear from our next
speaker.
Good evening for supervisors
again, my name is leonard
priestley.
I'm with the special police
officers association,
department of education
training and development.
But I want to share something
different with you.
I don't want you to think that
we're basically talking about
security.
And I also would like to
recognize this organization as
a way for 50 years of service
in san francisco 1974 that back
our first office.
>> we still have from 1974 also
last year to 24th we were able
to put a down payment on a
building on 14th and valencia a
folsom street.
And we're still there
struggling but we're still
in the building.
One of the things I want to
bring to your attention was the
great highway situation.
I brought one of the fliers
that we put out.
This is just a proposal and are
beginning just to let people
know what we're doing.
>> we've done a lot of things
over these past 50 years and we
really haven't gotten a credit
for it but that was okay.
>> we still a lot of people
through security went into law
enforcements sheriff's
department, fire department
and moved on from there.
We want to see how we can use a
space at the great highway to
put on an ongoing carnival to
remind us of please let at the
beach.
Most of you MAY not have been
around.
And whatever it happens to be
but we want to see how we can
create a proposal for all the
nonprofits who are going
through situations can take a
day to a carnival and raise so
much money in that way.
I have flowers to give to each
one of you.
So if you would take these
and anything that we can do
in our community we have office
on fillmore street because I
grew up on fillmore and we have
one on folsom street.
>> thank you, sir.
>> we'll come collect that from
you.
Let's welcome our next speaker
.
>> hello everyone.
My name is cheryl shanks
and I'm a member of mega black.
>> I wanted to say I wanted to
share something very positive
about dream keepers and what it
did for me and the tenderloin
community.
>> the project that I had been
working on for many years
called the soul station which
has manifested with the help of
dream keepers funds.
It will be the only black
restaurant in the whole
tenderloin.
>> it would not have happened.
It would not have happened if
it wasn't for guess a human
rights dream keepers fund in I
think that it's only fair that
the city start talking about
these kind of things in the
newspaper.
>> and instead of the bad
things.
>> I also would like to talk
about people being paid.
>> I worked and accountability.
>> I worked for the community
advisory committee.
First of all, I wanted to say
the city hired the person who
mismanaged and missed used the
money.
>> so why are people not being
paid?
Why are we being the fall guide
for people who and the people
who hired the people who
mismanaged the money are saying
we're not going to pay these
people even though we already
did the work?
>> I applied for that position
and I get the work of that
position if it was not okayed
by the district supervisor I
have nothing to do with that.
why am I not being paid?
Why am I not being paid?
>> why are other people not
being paid?
>> what about ourselves, the
world and our self identity as
black people in san francisco
that needs to be looked at
and I really thank you for your
comments.
Speakers speakers time is
concluded.
>> it will be very interesting
.
>> thank you for your comments.
Thank you.
All right.
Welcome.
>> good afternoon.
My name is cheryl thornton.
I stand before you today
in unwavering support of the
black employees alliance
because enough is enough.
Black workers in the city
and county of san francisco
have carried the weight of
systemic and structural racism
far too long.
We are not just talking about
isolated incidents.
We are also talking about the
pattern the most disciplined,
the last hired, the first
fired.
These are not just the texas
statistics.
They are people's families,
livelihoods and dignity.
Let's be clear this is not
equity.
This is not justice and this is
not acceptable.
>> we are calling on
mayor lurie and the board of
supervisors not with anger but
with urgency.
During his campaign,
mayor laurie stood before the
people of the city and promised
accountability.
He said he would hold his
administration to the highest
standards.
Now it's that time to keep that
promise.
MR. Mayor, your black employees
are watching.
San francisco is watching
and we are asking not just for
a seat at the table but for our
humanity to be recognized, for
our labor to be valued and our
rights to be protected.
And let us not forget this is
not just about a moral issue.
>> this is a legal one.
The city's own racial equity
ordinance ordinance which
mandates fairness in hiring
and promotion and discipline
and workplace culture is being
violated when black employees
are consistently targeted
and overlooked and pushed out.
It's not just unethical, it's
unlawful.
We need independent oversight.
We need transparent
and transparent hiring
and promotion and discipline.
Disciplinary practices.
And we need leadership that
doesn't just talk about equity
but it acts on it because if
black workers can't be safe,
respected and treated fairly
in the city like san francisco,
where can we go there?
Thank you.
Sheryl thornton for your
comments.
>> welcome.
The next speaker.
>> good afternoon supervisors.
My name is tom murphy and with
the jerry de committee
and friends of jerry garcia
amphitheater.
i'm just here to show support
for the jerry garcia street
sign coming out in excelsior
district.
Extremely proud.
It's happened on 415 day.
As a fellow native san
franciscan from the excelsior.
Just a few quick thank you's
supervisor cheyenne jan thank
you for introducing this
resolution all the board the
mayor jackie prager she was an
absolute she was wonderful to
work with patricia barraza
alondra from the youth
commission.
Luis from ymca.
Kathy mckee meyer and ben
leamon trixie garcia and the
whole jerry garcia family.
Mark allen from red light
management and of course all
the excelsior merchants
excelsior action group, the
excelsior mission merchants,
S.F. Clean city and the whole
excelsior district community
and of course jerry garcia.
As we celebrate 60 years of the
grateful dead this year it's a
whole six years that's pretty
monumental 20 years of the
jerry garcia amphitheater.
All the musicians playing this
music throughout the city, the
country and the world and of
course the millions of fans
around the world and I hope to
see all of you there at the
23rd annual jerry day on AUGUST
2nd.
Thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
All right.
Let's hear from our next
speaker.
>> please welcome.
Thank you.
Hi.
my name is celeste perrin.
I'm a day resident and a gun
violence prevention advocate
and activist.
>> I'm here to support
supervisor madeline's
resolution in support of
violence law hb 1363 and to
thank supervisor cheryl for
supporting it as well.
You know, in an environment
like we're in right now where
the federal government is so
openly hostile to common sense
gun laws and is actually
seeking to make us less safe
from gun violence, it's just so
important that we do everything
we can at the state and local
level to strengthen our laws
and our gun safety policy
in any way we can.
So I just want to encourage you
to keep doing that and I thank
you for introducing this
resolution.
>> thank you for your comments.
Welcome for our next speaker.
>> good afternoon supervisors.
My name is susan weisberg.
I'm here to urge you to pass
the resolution of support for
the california polluters pay
climate super bonneville that
is currently in the state
legislature.
We know that extreme fires like
those that ravaged the los
angeles area this pantawid past
winter extreme weather
conditions and sea level rise
are consequences of climate
change that is largely a result
of the burning of fossil fuels.
>> the companies that make
enormous profits from producing
and selling those fossil fuels
also know that and they have
known it for decades just as
the tobacco companies knew for
decades that cigarets were
killing people before they were
finally penalized with
anti-smoking legislation.
Yet it is every day
californians who are paying the
enormous costs of the climate
disasters those high profit
businesses have created.
It's more than time to make the
biggest fossil fuel polluters
pay for the consequences of
their actions.
For this reason the california
polluters pay climate superfund
bill transfers the major cost
burden from everyday taxpayers
to the polluters themselves.
It directs the california epa
to complete a climate cost
study to identify responsible
parties and to assess
contemporary fees.
>> it specifies that the funds
collected will mitigate, remedy
or prevent climate change costs
and harms polluters pay
superfund bills have been
passed in new york and vermont.
California must be next.
>> the fossil fuel companies
will fight this bill with
everything they have.
So a resolution of support from
the san francisco board of
supervisors will be a strong
message to the legislature that
californians want polluters to
stop getting off scot free.
Please pass the resolution of
support for the california
polluters pay climate superfund
bill and help it become law.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome to our next speaker
.
>> good afternoon supervisors.
My name's isabel penman.
I'm a resident of S.F.
and organizer with food
and water watch, the national
environmental advocacy
organization here in support of
passing the resolution.
>> I'll be voted on in support
of the make polluters pay
climate superfund bill in the
california legislature.
>> the L.A. Fires alone earlier
this year cost californians an
estimated $250 billion and it
will impact californians
and local economies for years
to come.
>> and while california faces a
46 billion budget deficit, the
fossil fuel companies behind
the crisis have been raking
in record profits.
The solution is clear polluters
must pay for their role
in climate disasters to lighten
the burden of ever rising
climate costs.
The california legislature
needs to pass this bill.
>> many californians already
are facing a massive cost of
living crisis.
They cannot and should not
shoulder this burden that
they're not responsible for.
We know that the fossil fuel
industry is responsible for
spewing 75% of global
greenhouse gas emissions
and almost 90% of all carbon
dioxide emissions.
>> we also know that they made
record profits drilling
and burning planet wrecking
fossil fuels.
>> exxonmobil and chevron alone
made 557 billion in just 2023.
I urge leaders here today to
stand with every day
californians, taxpayers,
homeowners who would otherwise
pay for these damages
and rising costs if we don't do
anything.
>> this climate superfund act
would raise up to hundreds of
billions of dollars some of it
going directly to san
francisco.
To protect californians
and build the infrastructure we
desperately need, it will lower
costs for protecting by
protecting taxpayers
and families from taking on the
burden themselves.
So again, I please urge you to
vote in support of the
resolution that stands with sb
684 and ab 1243 the climate
superfund bill.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome to the next speaker
.
>> hello.
My name is mia dreier.
I'm a san francisco resident
and I'm also here to urge you
to vote in support of the
polluters pay climate superfund
act.
And as you've already heard,
this bill has relates to both
the past and future of our
state.
So I am going to start with a
quick reminder about the past
about a day in SEPTEMBER 2020
when the sun didn't come up,
the sky was red and the air was
very difficult to breathe
because of wildfires happening
in or around the greater bay
area.
>> I am a speech therapist by
profession and in the days
and weeks that followed I
worked in a number of health
care facilities around the bay
area in the days and weeks that
followed that day I lost track
of the number of caregivers who
broke down in tears in front of
me because in addition to
supporting their loved ones
and caregiving for their loved
ones in the middle of covid
they now had concerns about
housing, about livelihood
and about further damage to
their loved one's health
through air quality and smoke
and other effects of the fires.
>> we talk in about this bill
and really big numbers billions
113 billion annual hundred $13
billion estimated annual
climate related cost to
californians by the year 2050
as has been mentioned, 250
billion in damages in the L.A.
Area from the recent fires.
But ultimately I'd like to
remind the board that this
burden falls on ordinary
californians who are made to
pay for the billions in profits
that are being accrued by the
largest fossil fuel companies
whose disinformation campaigns
are fueling the climate crisis.
This bill is an important step
on taking money from those
profiting and giving it back to
californians to support their
housing, to support their
livelihoods and to support
their health care.
And while we will continue to
deal with further climate
disasters and I urge you once
again to support the polluters
pay climate superfund act,
thank you very much for your
time.
>> thank you for your comments.
Welcome to the next speaker.
>> the recent shocking violence
erupted for the bouncer and the
angry drunken patrons of this
gay bar in the castro.
it illustrated how this castro
our pop market entertainment
JUNE is such an evil planet
that up up to gay boiling
block this city hall has been
informers for doing that for
years.
>> you are the example for some
street fair up your alley to
the nfl.
Well I respect is happening are
happening all the time I'm
in among the crowd and city you
know nothing let the city go
what low moral clubs jump for a
decade that's why all those
businesses are leaving san
francisco all still friends of
club out you should know better
than that.
Thank you for your comments.
Let's welcome our next speaker
please.
Hello, my name is elizabeth
smith phong and I live
in parkside.
I'm also here to speak
in support of the resolution
supporting sb 684 and hb 1243
of the polluters pay climate
superfund bill.
>> I'm the longtime san
francisco resident and I've
always been proud of our city's
leadership on climate change.
>> I also have a two year old
daughter and she's the reason I
started getting involved with
climate action.
>> so all of us in san
francisco lived through the
wildfires that other speakers
have mentioned and the past few
years and had to deal with that
poor air quality for weeks on
end.
>> I had to tape up my windows
to keep the smoke out and you
know now that I have kids I'm
worried about the possible
health effects if it were to
happen again.
And on top of that I just don't
want her generation or my
generation to have to pay for
the damage that polluters
and fossil fuel companies have
done.
So you know, we're all paying
the price for fossil fuel
pollution whether it's with our
health increased insurance
rates or with our children's
futures.
And this resolution is a really
powerful opportunity for san
francisco to keep leading on
climate change and to send a
message of support for a bill
that will really make a
difference for california.
>> thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Welcome to the next speaker.
>> good afternoon.
I'm doug nelson, resident of
san francisco for over 50
years.
Born and raised in california
and I'm also here in support of
the polluters pay climate super
fund.
>> you've heard a lot of
statistics here.
I think we all know that soup
the fossil fuel industry is a
major contributor to the global
climate change.
It's been proven it is the case
.
What MAY not be known is that
the how much how many trillions
of dollars that they've the
fossil fuel industry has been
able to reap from the fossil
fuel producing fossil fuels.
>> in in 2023 alone $244
billion were generated in 2033
and over $100 billion
in profits by chevron, exxon,
shell and bp and they all have
refineries and are all
represented here in our in our
area.
>> so what do they do with the
profits that goes to their
shareholders, goes to the stock
buybacks, it goes to ceos huge
salaries of $32 million on just
a 19% raise this year.
>> >> and who pays for it?
So as taxpayers we're at a
point in california now where
people cannot even get money to
pay they can't get insurance to
cover their homes, new homes or
they're getting policies taken
away.
Myself over 25% raise in my
homeowner's insurance.
So I'm here because we need for
the fossil fuel industry to do
their duty, do their due
diligence.
They known this for years of
what they're causing this
environment across the globe
and we need to we need to make
sure that they pay their fair
share.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments
and your support.
Thank you for your comments,
sir.
>> we're going to welcome our
next speaker.
>> good afternoon.
My name is alonzo habiger
mccabe and I'm a district five
constituent in san francisco.
>> alana, can you talk directly
into that microphone?
>> just pull it close to you.
Yes, if you can.
There you go.
Sorry about that.
>> I'm also here to speak
in support of the board
resolution to support the make
polluters pay climate super
fund bill in the state
legislature.
I've seen the effects of
climate change firsthand from
wildfire smoke to heat waves
and flooding during atmospheric
river storms in san francisco.
I've had friends lose their
homes in the paradise fire
and more recently in the L.A.
Fires.
As a lifelong environmentalist
and environmental engineer, I
know the effects of climate
change will only get worse
and will continue to cost the
california taxpayers billions
of dollars.
That's why I'm here to urge the
board to support the
resolution.
It's time to send a message of
support to the state government
and make polluters pay.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome to our next speaker
.
>> hi.
My name is nancy keith with
hope.
I'm a resident of san francisco
fillmore district.
I am originally from kenya
and appreciate this country
that gave us second chances
in life and we have a lot to
say.
>> thank you to the city of san
francisco to america but of
late it has become a dumpster.
>> it has become a very
disgusting place especially
when we have surpassed our
children in public schools here
where they are indoctrinated
propaganda taught.
>> I have a lot of information
here pulling out from what my
kids are being taught in san
francisco high schools.
This is not information that
children can be able to go to
ivy league schools where they
are being taught 200 gender
ideologies which is so
nonsensical to us who are
african conservative parents
and we are also very
stigmatized.
First of all big up to daniel
lurie.
We supported him and thank you
for all the amazing things he's
doing to the city.
>> bilal mahmood is our
supervisor in the fillmore.
The african community has been
stigmatized for years.
We are stigmatized by the
african-american community
where we don't get the funding
that trickles down to the
african community.
A lot of african parents
actually taking their children
back to africa because we are
not welcomed in the spaces
where we can be able to do
programing that help in our
african culture.
>> we brought the kenyan
PRESIDENT Here.
He was not acknowledged by a
black london breed.
We hated.
So bilal mahmood we are asking
for an african cultural center.
>> mamadou well we do a lot of
programing and we need to come
and dodge their education
system here and thank you to
trump for dismantling the
education system.
We need the school vouchers so
we can take our kids to private
schools teaching the kids on
patriotism and not the garbage
of what is being taught.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> let's hear from our next
speaker.
Please welcome.
>> happy for one five day board
of supervisors.
Great speech, nancy.
You know, I think it's time we
prioritize the well-being of
women and children in our
community.
>> she has a point.
>> you know, kids in school
they should be learning abcs
one, two, three playing outside
instead they're being
sexualized and taught adult
materials they should not be
exposed to.
>> and kids aren't just
suffering at the schools on
their way to schools as we all
seen.
They're forced to navigate the
trenches which are filled with
tents and bodies broken
government issued crack pipes.
There's 20 plus people using
fentanyl at the playground
and ever since they started
cracking down key crack
and down on sixth and market
and 24th in mission the
honduras vignale dealers have
adapted.
>> they're using electric
scooters now to circle around
our playground and our problem
areas.
>> they are more mobile
peddlers of death phenols a
form of chemical warfare on the
american people comes from
china across the southern
border these honduras phenol
dealers need to be deported not
given the same rights as
indigenous native americans
when children are walking to
school in san francisco
and they're tripping over
bodies and needles and their
species everywhere.
That's a problem when children
are playing on the playground
and there are 20 plus people
using fennel.
That's a problem you guys are
supposed to be the leaders of
our community and I'd like to
see as much vigor for the
fentanyl genocide happening
right in front of city hall at
the same amount as you guys
virtue signal for every little
thing while everything gets
progressively worse,
progressive policy is making
everything progressively worse
harm reductions causing more
harm.
Forget the gentleman's name
last name schultz.
He said downtown is for drug
users.
He overdosed this morning.
He's no longer with us.
You can't blame that on
republicans.
You guys, there's a civil war
happening in the democrat
party.
You got moderate versus the far
left but you're both wrong.
>> you guys need to take a look
in the mirror and take a walk
at the bottom of the hill.
You're living on top of the
hill where everything's fine
and dandy.
>> thank you for your comments.
>> see you next tuesday.
Let's welcome our next speaker
.
Hello.
My name is augustin gara.
Been working with the city
and county of san francisco for
13 years now.
I love this city but I also
represent a lot of employees.
I'm a proud union member of the
mental health chapter.
I'm a PRESIDENT And a steward.
And I just want to say I'm
standing here in solidarity for
support of our black employee
alliance.
They I have been representing a
lot of employees in my chapter.
And more often than not I'm
representing them
and disciplinary issues
and more often than not they're
people of color.
And it's just wrong and unfair
that the cost of living in this
city has gotten ridiculous.
It's pushed pushed out a lot of
us working families and really
the red lining is still
existing.
The opportunity to this
american dream is not what it
used to be and I just wanted to
be here to make sure and make
it clear to you all that our
union is vigilant and we're
ready to meet with the mayor.
Lori we heard at the psc
meeting that he extended his
olive branch.
He is willing to meet with
unions and to start talking
with us.
I also suggest he talk with
this powerful black employee
alliance that is creating an
important important cause for
change.
We need to have more diversity
in the city, not less.
And by making it harder
and harder for us to get jobs.
That is not the way to go about
things.
>> hiring freezes while
contracting out is not okay.
i will leave the last 30s to
just say that I'm a unionist.
I'm proud.
I love this city and I want to
see it do better and do better
for all of us workers no matter
what our color is.
So please enough with this
bias.
Please enough with the cronyism
and nepotism.
Stop hiring your friends
and family.
Hire people that can do the job
and are capable.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> let's welcome our next
speaker.
>> hi, my name is liam mciver.
I live in d6.
I'll try to get through this
without crying after that.
>> this is what I wish my
supervisor a supervisor would
say.
I want a state of emergency
declared in d six for being a
humanitarian crisis crippling
poverty in the shadows of
billionaires skyscrapers is
unacceptable.
We must redistribute survival
resources like housing to
seriously address this issue at
its root.
We need to defund the police.
We have only been increasing
the budget despite the horrific
violence against our
communities and particular can
start black and brown
communities r t l g b q plus
community.
Our sex worker community our
disabled community are
undocumented community and our
neurodivergent community.
There is no question that they
are also mismanaging funds
repeatedly if increasing sfpd
budget solve societal problems
we'd be living in a perfect
society by now.
But it doesn't and we don't.
Let's be fiscally smart
and invest our money
in solutions that have been
shown to work like education
and basic and versal income
and reparations.
>> transgender rights are human
rights.
There will never be an lgb
without the t and those that
foolishly try.
I'm fighting for you for your
right to gender affirming
health care for your right to
live life however you want no
matter what any cis person MAY
think for your right to walk
down the street without fear
for your right to be housed
and fed, for your right to be
employed and treated with
respect in the workplace for
your right to happiness.
>> your children do not deserve
to be used as pawns
in politics.
They do not deserve to be to
grow up in poverty conditions
and so san francisco, including
myself must lift you out of
poverty with the urgency this
calls for when our neighborhood
is well nourished instead of
impoverished that will be
reflected on the streets
and sidewalks.
>> we must also seriously
invest in free quality
childcare for your children.
>> now homeless people deserve
to have homes no matter what
your worth this your life is
worth saving no matter the
balance in your bank account.
You matter and we want you to
stay in san francisco housed we
must live.
>> transpeople must live.
Thank you, lia.
Macgyver for your comments.
Welcome.
Our next speaker.
>> if there are any other
members of the public in the
chamber who haven't yet
addressed the board during
general public comment please
come on up.
Otherwise this gentleman will
be our last speaker.
>> hello, my name is richard t
peterson.
I'm from snowy valley and I'm
not here to talk about permits.
I am here to talk about ocean
beach and I'm a former surfer.
Since 2020 I haven't been able
to surf but I always like
driving down the between
and and say gary on the on the
highway to to see what the
ocean look like.
>> now however my dog and I
took the queen tara bus down to
ocean beach and my dog sly
hates the water even though
he's a yellow lab with webbed
feet.
But the problem was the bus
just drops you off and then
when you want to leave it
expects you to go across the
street to some sort of foreign
location.
>> why is there not good access
for people at the beach at both
ends?
Take the gary bus and it
doesn't drop you off at the
beach anymore.
It drops you off up at the top
of the sea drop.
Anyway, that's my quip for the
day.
I love taking muni.
muni is better than it's ever
been.
It's cleaner.
They're doing a little prob
problems with the timing but
it's great and that's all.
>> I love san francisco.
Thank you for your comments.
>> all right MR. PRESIDENT.
All right.
Public comment is now closed.
>> MADAM Clerk let's go to our
for adoption without committee
reference agenda items 4345
items 40 through 45 these items
were introduced for adoption
without committee reference.
A unanimous vote is required
for adoption of a resolution on
first reading today.
Alternatively, a member MAY
require a resolution on first
reading to go to committee
supervisor fielder thank you.
>> I'd like to request the
sever item 41.
I don't see anyone else putting
themselves in the queue so
MADAM Clerk can you call the
roll on the balance of the
items other than 41 that would
be items 4042 4344 and 45
supervise her chin chin eyes
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor engardio
and engardio I supervisor
fielder fielder I supervisor
mahmood mahmood I supervisor
mandolin hi mandolin I
supervisor melgar I melgar I
supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
and supervisor walden are
walton I there are lebanese
without objection these
resolutions are adopted and the
motion is approved and then
MADAM Clerk could you please
call item 41 item 41 this is a
resolution to support
california state senate bill
number 684 introduced by
senator carolyn miniver.
Miniver excuse me and assembly
bill number 1243 introduced by
assembly member don adams to
address the climate crisis
in california by shifting the
burden of increased taxpayer
costs away from california
residents and small businesses
to fossil fuel companies that
have created the climate
crisis.
>> supervisor fielder thank you
PRESIDENT Colleagues, this bill
which is in the california
legislature now is intended to
make the largest fossil fuel
companies rather than
california taxpayers pay the
enormous costs of the extreme
fires, extreme weather
conditions and sea level rise
that are consequences of
climate change caused largely
by the burning of fossil fuels.
This bill will direct cal epa
to complete a climate cost
study, identify responsible
parties and assess compensatory
fees and use the collected fees
to fund projects and programs
to mitigate, remedy or prevent
climate change costs and harms
our support for these two bills
comes at an opportune moment as
the bill just passed through
the senate environmental policy
committee last week is going to
the assembly natural resources
committee next monday and will
go through the assembly
judiciary committee as well as
the senate judiciary committee
for a hearing sometime in JUNE.
San francisco assembly member
haney and senator wiener are
both coauthors of this bill.
>> I thank them as well as the
more than 150 organizations
including the sierra club of
california sunrise movement
and many others for supporting
this bill and for all of their
organizing to ensure that the
fossil fuel polluters pay for
their devastation on our
climate.
>> I would also like to thank
my co sponsors supervisors
melgar mahmood chen, walton
chan sadr and mendelson.
>> thank you so much.
>> thank you.
Supervisor fielder I don't see
anyone else on the roster so I
think we can take item 41.
Same house, same call without
objection the resolution is
adopted.
>> and then MADAM Clerk, do we
have any imperative agenda
items?
>> there are none to report.
MR. PRESIDENT.
>> all right.
Could you please read the
in memoriam?
Today's meeting will be
adjourned in memory of the
following beloved individuals
on behalf of supervisor fielder
for the late larry curtis on
behalf of board PRESIDENT
Mandolin for the late scott
nielsen and on a motion made by
supervisor sartor and mahmood.
And on behalf of the entire
board of supervisors for the
late teller to appear.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
I believe that brings us to the
end of our agenda do we have
any further business before us
today?
>> that concludes our business
for today.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
>> as there's no further